<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great concern and zeal of a loyal people for a good king's preservation in the hazards of war. And the duty of such a people opened and enforced, in one of our monthly-fasts in a country parish. By the minister thereof.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212854</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825495</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41888)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1760:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great concern and zeal of a loyal people for a good king's preservation in the hazards of war. And the duty of such a people opened and enforced, in one of our monthly-fasts in a country parish. By the minister thereof.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43 [i.e. 44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Jonathan Robinson, at the Golden-Lion in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P. 43, 44 misnumbered 44, 43.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29877:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi rend="blackletterType">Great Concern and Zeal</hi> OF A LOYAL PEOPLE FOR A GOOD KING'S PRESERVATION In the HAZARDS of WAR.</p>
            <p>And the Duty of ſuch a People opened and enforced, In one of our MONTHLY-FASTS in a Country Pariſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Miniſter thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi rend="blackletterType">Ionathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden-Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29877:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29877:2"/>
            <head>To all that ſincerely fear God, and honour King WILLIAM and Queen MARY.</head>
            <p>THE Word of Authority to us, is, <hi>To your Prayers;</hi> as the Word of a Commander to his Souldiers, <hi>To your Arms.</hi> The Weapons of our Warfare are not Carnal but Spiritual, Mighty through God, to the pulling down of the ſtrong Holds of Satan; not only in the Hearts of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers, and Enemies of the Goſpel, battering, yea, caſting down Imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the Knowledg of God, and bringing into Captivity every Thought to the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Chriſt, <hi>(2 Cor. 10.4, 5.)</hi> but the ſame ſpiritual Weapons are mighty againſt all the viſible Armies, and ſtrong-Holds of the Devil, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Vice-Royes, the declared Enemies of the true Church of Chriſt, yea, and of Mankind alſo, according to the extent of their Power. What mighty things are recorded to be done by One of thoſe Weapons of our Warfare, mighty through God, in ſenſible Weakneſs, and Self-diſtruſt? And what ſhall I more ſay? <hi>For the Time will fail me to tell of</hi> Gideon, <hi>and of</hi> Barak, <hi>and of</hi> Sampſon, <hi>and of</hi> Jephtha, <hi>of</hi> David <hi>alſo and</hi> Samuel, <hi>and of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who through Faith ſubdued Kingdoms,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heb. 11.32, 33.</hi> Take notice, how the Prophets, Men of Peace, are enroll'd among the Men of War. And no wonder that when Victories and Conqueſts, even over Kingdoms, are attributed to Faith, that then the Prophets ſhould have an eminent place among the greateſt Men of greateſt Name. And this Power of Faith is not loſt, but wants Exerciſe, for <hi>this is the Victory which overcometh the World, even your Faith, 1</hi> John <hi>5.4, 5.</hi> And that which overcometh the World, and that mighty evil Spirit in it, can ſubdue a Kingdom at any time, when God pleaſeth, and the time of its deſtruction is come. This Faith is exerciſed in Prayer; and by Prayer, winning, and engaging the mighty God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> the Lord of Hoſts, to be on our ſide: Our Enemies cannot ſtand before us; they ſhall fall and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, the ſtrong ſhall be as Tow. <hi>One Man ſhall chaſe a thouſand, and two ten thouſand,</hi> Deut. <hi>32.30.</hi> Joſ. <hi>23.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of God is both beautiful and formidable, Cant. <hi>6.4. Terrible as an Army with Banners.</hi> Her Majeſty and Statelineſs is ſet forth, as an Army with Banners; and her exceeding great Power in her Faith, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <hi>Believers, in regard of the Power of their Faith, are more terrible than Armies, ſaith Excellent Mr.</hi> Durham. If one <hi>Jacob</hi> as a Prince prevailed, and by his Strength had Power with God, <hi>Hoſ. 12.3, 4.</hi> What cannot many do, that weep and make Supplications? What cannot an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Believers do? What cannot an Army do, that by an united Faith, with Sighs and Weeping, take Heaven by violence? Faithleſs, ſpiritleſs, faint, formal Prayers, put into rank and file, and diſplayed in the fineſt Eloquence,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29877:3"/>do no Service at all, ſuch Prayers do but beat the Air. That ſame Language in which God ſpeaks to us, is the moſt proper for us to pray to God; that Word by which God worketh Faith in us, is that which beſt ſuiteth the Prayer of plain-hearted Faith.</p>
            <p>It is an Obſervation of Eminent Mr. <hi>Charnock,</hi> which deſerves to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven on our Hearts. <q>When God would do any mighty Work in the World, he ſtirs up his People to pray for it; and their Prayers by his own appointment have a mighty influence upon the Government of the World: for when they come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in behalf of his Church in general, he doth indulge them a greater Liberty and Boldneſs, and as it were a kind of Authority over him, than upon other occaſions of their own. Iſa. <hi>45.11. Thus ſaith the Lord, The Holy One of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and his Maker, Ask of me things to come concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Sons, and the Work of my Hands command ye me.</hi> God would be more poſitively,<note place="margin">Treat. of Provid. <hi>p. 71. Fol.</hi>
                  </note> confidently, and familiarly dealt with about the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of his Sons, though they were things to come to paſs in after-Ages— <hi>Rev. 8.3, 4.</hi> The great Changes in the World, are an Anſwer to thoſe Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which are offered unto God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Holy Brethren! The Work of God hath been very great in ſome eminent part of the World, in ſome Countries and Kingdoms; and the Prayers of the Faithful have prevailed much: But was there ever at any one time ſo great a Work as is now a doing in our Days? Are not the great Affairs of the Sons of God in all Proteſtant Churches, I ſay in all Proteſtant Churches, drawing near to a Determination? The Iſſue of this War is like to be the Riſe or Fall, not only of many in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but of all the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, confederate in the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Jeſus Chriſt. O then, is not this the time for us to be of one Heart and Soul, deeply humbled, ſincerely mourning, crying and ſighing for the Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are yet in our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Cities and Countries weeping and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Supplication, and with the moſt reverent and awful Adoration, make us bold with the Higheſt Majeſty of the Holy One, the Saviour, in a time of trouble, as he alloweth us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Monſieur Jurieu</hi> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of Prophecies, and others.</note> Even to command him concerning his Sons, and the time to come, which many of his Servants wait for; and ſay, as <hi>Luther,</hi> Fiat vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas mea, <hi>Let my Will be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Holy Brethren, partakers of the Heavenly Calling; Give me leave to engage you to be more abundant in the fervent Prayers of Faith, and of true Penitent, reformed in Heart and Life. Conſider how much of this great Work lies upon you at this time. Who can tell what your Prayers may do, under God, by his appointment. The Proclamation for theſe Faſts reacheth to the Realm of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed.</hi> O that all from ſixteen to ſixty in theſe Bounds were fit for Prayer; to bear Arms, theſe ſpiritual Arms! O then, how might we hope, that even ſhe that tarrieth at Home, and is fervent in her Cloſet, may divide the Spoils, of the greater Spoiler, of all he can lay hands on. But O, how weak are we? how divided? how unprepared? What Help can we look for from them that are diſaffected to the King and Queen,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29877:3"/>and troubled at this glorious Revolution? How do they murmur that God ſhould do what ſeemeth him good, for his Peoples Good! How many are there that do not as much as appear to Faſt! How many are for the Liturgy of <hi>James</hi> (not the Apoſtle's which hath been reputed ſpurious by many of our moſt Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divines and Biſhops, but) the Apoſtate's! How many, half, yea half-quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obſervers of thoſe Holy and ſolemn Days! How like are theſe to old Bottles! How many of thoſe who ſeem well affected to the Government, are groſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſenſual and profane, unreformed, unrefined from their Lees! What can theſe do? What ill-favoured, irreverent, what cold and dead, what broken Work do many make! ſo that we have cauſe to fear the Divine abhorrence of our Faſting. How far may a Man ride before he can ſee one Sinner, whoſe Heart and Life is reformed according to the Word of God, after our many monthly Days of Faſting? If a Poll could be taken of them that are for, or againſt, or are wary Neuters, whether ever God and Chriſt, or their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſhould be found in the beſt ſide? All muſt be excluded from voting right, who do not lift up holy Hands to God in Prayer; ſo that from the Land's End, even to the Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> we can make no more than a <hi>Gideon</hi>'s Army. But yet I hope there are enow to make an Army, too ſtrong for all the Enemies of our Faith, Religion, Peace and Government. Be therefore of good Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, wait on the Lord, and he ſhall ſtrengthen your Heart, all ye that hope in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Encourage our ſelves in the Lord our God, were our Extremities greater and more than they are. And conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Is not God on our Side? O let us humbly wreſtle with his Majeſty to riſe for his own Glory, for <hi>David</hi>'s ſake, for <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s ſake! what will our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the Heathen ſay?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Hath not God prevented us with his loving-Kindneſs? Did we by our Prayers call in our Deliverer? Did not God put it into his Heart before we knew of it? Have we not ſeen when we faſted and prayed, it went well with us? for the Honour of God, for the Honour of his Ordinance, for Prayer's-ſake (deſpiſed, blaſphemed Prayers-ſake) I was glad to hear it was the poor praying People of <hi>Ireland</hi> that ſaved <hi>London-derry,</hi> that made the Men of <hi>Inniskillin</hi> more than Men, and not our Gallant <hi>Dammees</hi> and <hi>Hectors.</hi> Pray on to the laſt Breath; pray to the laſt drop of Tears. Give not up ſo great and ſo good a Cauſe for loſt, it is all in the Hand of God, our God, truſt him.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Pray on: there are more for us than there be againſt us: Is not God for us? Are not Angels for us? Do not the Souls under the Altar ſolicite God, and cry, <hi>How long, Lord, Holy and True,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>doſt thou not avenge our Blood on them that dwell on the Earth?</hi> I beſeech you obſerve this, that they who are our Enemies now, are they who have ſhed the Blood of the Saints. We are ſure that God will avenge the Blood of his Servants, and hear the Prayers of his Saints in Heaven, and on Earth. The Lord never denied to hear their Prayers, he hath only delayed. <hi>Andit was ſaid unto them, that they ſhould
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29877:4"/>reſt yet for a little ſeaſon, until their fellow-Servants alſo, and their Brethren that ſhould be killed as they were, ſhould be fulfilled.</hi> Some have written, and others believe this late, is the laſt Perſecution of the Churches in <hi>France</hi> at leaſt: and if ſo, that the Number of them that ſhould be Killed, is fulfilled; then we ſhall ſhortly ſing, as <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> and the People did, <hi>For his Mercy endureth for ever, 2</hi> Chron. <hi>20.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Pray, believing in him to whom you pray, and knowing againſt whom you pray; Is he not a bloody mercileſs Perſecutor, who can ſet him out in his Garments dy'd in Blood? and hath not God, ſaid, <hi>He hath ordained his Arrows againſt the Perſecutors?</hi> plead that with God, <hi>Pſal. 7.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Who do we pray for? Are they not God's own People, the Apple of his Eye? or hath God not one ſmall R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nant left? Remember the Prayer of <hi>Nehemiah; Now theſe are thy Servants, and thy People, whom thou haſt redeemed with thy great Power, and by thy ſtrong Hand.</hi> Nehem. <hi>1.4,</hi> to <hi>10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> Argue from the very Strength and Greatneſs of our Enemy. O ſay our Men of Reaſon and Thoughts, (Men like the cowardly Spies of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> who diſcouraged the People) How powerful is <hi>France!</hi> How Great that King! How wiſe his Counſel! How mighty are his Armies! How ſtrong at Sea! How well diſciplined! what an Advantage hath he, who is one in united Councils, before-hand with his Enemies in the time of Year, whereas the Confederates are ſlow in Reſolutions and Preparations? He'll hold them in play, he'll tire them out! And what will not this Great Man do! Yea, Are theſe things true? is this the ſenſe of Men, wiſe Men, moſt Men! Be it ſo. Yet for all this, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l he the Army of <hi>Zera</hi> the <hi>Ethiopian;</hi> Let us cry to the Lord as <hi>Aſa</hi> did.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 14.9.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, it is nothing with thee to help, whether with many, or with them that have no Power; Help us, O Lord our God, for we reſt on thee, and in thy Name we go againſt this multitude; thou art the Lord our God, let not Men prevail againſt Thee.</hi> Let us wait upon God, and take an Argument from the ſtrength of our Enemies, Pſal. <hi>59.9. Becauſe of his Strength, let us wait on thee; for God is my Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have a God hearing Prayer to pray unto; we have a good Cauſe; all is in Danger; we have great Encouragements; O let us ſay, He hath delivered, and we truſt be will not only deliver, but proſper. O then let us pray for a praying Heart! And pray every Day, without ceaſing. And that firſt for our King and Queen, that they may have the whole Armour of God to put on, the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, that in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs of their Hearts they do all they do, that they may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fall into the ſlippery and pernitious Steps of evil Kings. Let us pray for them, that they may inherit an Everlaſting Kingdom, that endeavour to make ours ſo happy. Many do labour to fright us more with the King's Succeſſes, than with the return of their idolized Image; as if he would be as abſolute, as high for Prerogatives as any of his Predeceſſors. What Confuſions he will make, ſay others, in the beſt Church in the World; and much more. Whereas the great fear is, that he will do more for God than most of his Predeceſſors. Men are mightily afraid of loſing their Pluralities, their Ceremonies, their Sins. Let us pray for the preſervation of our Lamps, the free Progreſs of the Goſpel, the Advancement of Religion and Godlineſs into High Places, for a painful Preaching, exemplary Miniſtry, for the ſaving and ſanctifying Proteſtant Churches, for healing of Breaches; in a word, for Grace, Mercy, Peace. And when we have pray'd, to the pouring out of our Hearts, let us not truſt to our Prayers beyond God's Promiſes, but ſtay our ſelves upon the Rock of our Salvation: To whom be Might and Dominion for ever. Salvation to our God. <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29877:4"/>
            <head>The <hi>Great Concern</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> of a Loyal People for a Good Warlike KING, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Sam. 21.15, 16, 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Moreover, the Philiſtines had yet War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> went down, and his Servants with him, and fought againſt the Philiſtines; and <hi>David</hi> waxed faint. And <hi>Iſhbi-benob,</hi> which was of the Sons of the Giant, (the weight of whoſe Spear weighed three hundred Shekels of Braſs in weight) he being girded with a new Sword, thought to have ſlain <hi>David.</hi> But <hi>Abiſhai</hi> the Son of <hi>Zeruiah</hi> ſuccoured him, and ſmote the Philiſtine, and killed him. Then the Men of <hi>David</hi> ſware unto him, ſaying, Thou ſhalt go no more out with us to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, that thou quench not the Light of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are a very remarkable plece of Story, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in it ſelf, and therefore I need not look upon what goes before it in this Chapter. I crave your earneſt attention to the Matter I intend to handle for your Inſtruction this part of the Day, and have but patience till I come to the Application, then I hope you will ſee, that what I ſhall deliver to you, will be very ſuitable to the Work and Duty of this Day; and not only ſo, but will direct you what to do every Day, till God ſhall turn our Faſts into Thankſgivings. The true Reaſon of my chuſing this Text, and that upon this Solemn Day, which requires an extraordinary ſeriouſneſs, with the Application of the whole ſtrength of our Hearts, and exerciſe of every Grace, is not at all to flatter, much leſs to idolize our King and Queen, which would be the worſt of Services to them, and to our ſelves, by provoking God to quench the Light of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but really to ſhew you as plainly, and as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly as I can, how deeply our Hearts ſhould be affected with our own Condition, how earneſt we ſhould be with God to preſerve our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governours, and eſpecially our King in the Labours and Dangers of this War; and how we ſhould behave our ſelves under all thoſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances under which the Sovereign and over-ruling Providence of the infinitely Wife and Almighty God hath ſubjected us. And I was moved to theſe Conſiderations, which I ſhall commend to you, by the great
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29877:5"/>Thoughts of Heart which poſſeſs many honeſt, religious, and tender Perſons. Why, ſay they, will our King hazard his Perſon in this War, who is in danger, not only from the Craft and Malice of the open Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in the Field, but Treachery even in his Camp? Why will the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Kingdom let him? What will become of us, if we ſhould be ſo unhappy as to loſe Him, in this unſettled and diſtracted State, when there are ſo many ſecret Diſcontents, and ſuch open Talk? Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, we cannot be too much concerned for the Safety of their Sacred Perſons, the Peace of theſe Kingdoms, and the Preſervation of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion both at Home and Abroad. The Glory of God, the Kingdom of our Lord Jeſus, and the Salvation of our Souls, by the Means of Grace, are as much concerned in the Succeſs of this War, as ever at any time to any People. This War is not a War for outward Peace and Liberty, nor for Glory and Renown, for Riches and Trade, or any other tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral End or Intereſt only, but for the true Intereſt of the Kingdom of God among us, and of the Proteſtant People of God in all Nations where they are, or ſoon will be in danger, if God doth not ſhew himſelf to be on our Side. There are many Intereſts of many Princes and People in this one Bottom, and all united in one King, and ſubmitted to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct under God: If theſe ſhould be divided, we ſhould be weakned and fail; but if he ſhould miſcarry, we muſt needs ſink for a time, and many Countries ſuffer Shipwrack; and then not only the Eſtates, Liberties, Properties, Bodies, and Lives, but precious Souls, and the Ark of God would fall into the Power of the Cruel. The Philiſtines would ſoon over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run our Land; and they who ſeem to wiſh for their coming, would feel the Miſeries of their coming, as ſoon as they who faſt and pray with all ſincerity to keep them out, and be leſs able to endure them. If the Light of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould be quenched, O how tempeſtuous would it be round about! What a Day would it be of Gloomineſs and thick Darkneſs! O, far be it from thoſe who deſire that Evil Day ever to ſee it come! may they all go to their Graves in peace, before that Inundation of Woes and Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries break down our Banks. 'Tis true, we have more to loſe now at once than ever our Forefathers had; and therefore when we conſider our Sins, we have more cauſe to fear than ever. But let this comfort and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us to offer up ſtrong Prayers and Cries to the God of Heaven, to God our Saviour, that the Glory of God's Truth, Mercy and Grace, being ſo ſpecially and imminently concerned in this War, that his Wiſdom and Power will the more ſincerely appear for the preſervation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Light of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Call up Faith and Hope to put forth all their ſtrength into thoſe Prayers which go not out of feigned Lips. O for a ſtrong Faith at the head of our Godly Sorrows and Humiliation for Sin this Day! O for the Aſſiſtance of the mighty Spirit of Prayer, and Supplication to ſend up, yea, to carry our fervent Prayers to Heaven. Is the Spirit of God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29877:5"/>departed from his praying, wreſtling <hi>Jacobs</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and gone to our Enemies Hearts? Is God, is the Ark of God in their Camp? Hath not God prepared his Arrows againſt the Perſecutors? What inhumane Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions are the greateſt of them guilty of! But as my Thoughts run on this String of Hope, I am checked by the ſight of the great and many Sins of theſe Kingdoms, for which God might bring us under the Sword of our Enemies; and even deliver up the Ark, the Church, into their hands. O that every Congregation were weeping and mourning before the Lord this Day, and caſting away our Iniquities! O that this Day were a Day of confeſſing and forſaking thoſe Sins for which God might juſtly hide his Face from us! O that we were exerciſing of Revenge upon our ſelves for all our Abominations! O that we were ſighing and crying for all the Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations done in the midſt of our <hi>Jeruſalem!</hi> and that all in their Places would become zealous for the Glory of God, reſolving every one to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify his own Sins, diſarming the Traitors againſt God, Church and State, in his own Heart, and ſetting themſelves againſt Sin in others, that God may be reconciled to us, and intreated for the Kingdom! But yet, as bad as we are, are we not God's People? Are there not ſome Fifties among us, for whoſe ſake God will ſpare us? But not to inſiſt upon ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for Hope, let us build upon one, it is a ſtrong and a ſtanding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, by inverting the Word of God, and humbly turning it upon him, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, I do not this for your ſakes, O Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>but for my holy Name's ſake.—Not for your ſakes, do I this, ſaith the Lord God, be it known unto you: be aſhamed and confounded for your own ways, O Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.22, 32. When we have leaſt to ſay, and have no Reaſons to plead taken from our ſelves, we have moſt to ſay, and the moſt prevailing Argument to urge by Faith, taken from the free Mercy of God, and the Glory of his great Name. O let us take Courage, and come boldly to the Throne of Grace, and ſay,<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.4. Jer. 14.7.</note> 
               <hi>Save us for thy Mercies ſake. O Lord, though our Iniquities teſtify againſt us, do thou it for thy Name's ſake, for our back-ſlidings are many, we have ſinned againſt thee. O Lord, hear, O Lord, forgive, O Lord, hearken and do, defer not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 9.19.</note> 
               <hi>for thine own ſake, O my God, for the City and People that are called by thy Name. Not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name give Glory, for thy Mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>and for thy Truth's ſake. Wherefore ſhould the Heathen ſay,</hi> (the French and Iriſh, the Philiſtines, the Enemies of the Lord that have ſo reproached him, that have deſtroyed all his Tabernacles in the Land ſay,) <hi>Where is now their God?</hi> Such an Encouragement as this may quicken us to a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Attention to the Word of God, and put Life into our Prayers, when moſt dejected under the ſenſe of our Sins. And ſo now I come to the Words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In this part of ſacred Story, we read of another War between a proud,<note place="margin">Zech. 9.6.</note> unquiet, idolatrous, ſuperſtitious People, and <hi>David, ver.</hi> 5. The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29877:6"/>had been often deſtroyed and conquered by the Sword of <hi>David,</hi> and yet they begin another War with <hi>David,</hi> as the Phraſe doth inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate; <hi>And the Philiſtines had yet War again with</hi> Iſrael; as if they began it, and provoked <hi>Iſrael</hi> unto it: We read not what the particular Cauſe of the War was, it might be from inveterate Hatred, from Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Religion; for the Philiſtines, like our Papiſts, had their Images in the Battel of <hi>Baal Perazim;</hi> and as their Images could not help them, ſo neither could they ſave their Images;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 5.21.</note> or it might be Impatience of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge that might ſtir them up, and they thought themſelves ſtrong enough to overcome and over-run <hi>Iſrael;</hi> or they might promiſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Life of <hi>David,</hi> having a ſelf-confident vain-glorious Giant, <hi>Iſhbi-benob,</hi> who might brag as well as think of killing <hi>David.</hi> It is a righteous Judgment of God upon the inveterate Enemies of his People, which they ſee not, that they will not be quiet in their Poſſeſſions, but after many Overthrows they will be making Wars againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>And</hi> David <hi>went down, and his Servants with him, and fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Philiſtines;</hi> it ſeems to be a defenſive as well as a lawful War, to go down againſt the Philiſtines, and not to ſtay for their coming into the Land of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> they were the beginners of the War, and <hi>David</hi> doth wiſely chooſe the Seat of the War, which might be moſt convenient, the further off from home, and the nearer the Enemies Country the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. An experienced valiant King will neither refuſe nor delay to fight againſt the Enemies of God's People, and his Kingdom, when there is juſt Cauſe and Provocation given.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>And</hi> David <hi>waxed faint;</hi> he grow in Years, and was much decayed in Strength, or tired and weakned with the Wars. This Circumſtance affords us many Obſervations. 1. The Wars and Troubles in a King's Reign, are no Sign or Indication of, and ſhould create no Suſpitions in any Men, of the Weakneſs or Badneſs of his Title to the Kingdom. Never had King a better or a clearer Title to a Kingdom than <hi>David</hi> had, appointed and deſigned of God, elected and made by the People, and anointed: Nay, the Malice of the Philiſtines boil'd and ſwell'd, and broke out into an open Attempt and War againſt <hi>David,</hi> when they heard he was anointed; 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.17. <hi>But when the Philiſtines heard that they had anointed</hi> David <hi>King over</hi> Iſrael, <hi>all the Philiſtines came to ſeek</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid: — <hi>And ſpread themſelves in the Valley of</hi> Rephaim, v. 18. Is <hi>David</hi> anointed? has he taken the Kingdom upon him? then before he is ſettled in his Throne, we will ſeek him. This Policy was equal to the Malice, while the Government was young and tender, as ſome here ſaid of ours, and the Factions of the Kingdom not inwardly healed: but the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God turned this to <hi>David</hi>'s Glory, by giving him the Victory, they and their Images fell into his Hands, <hi>ver.</hi> 20, 21. When God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns a King, and gives him a Throne, they who riſe againſt him, riſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29877:6"/>and war againſt God himſelf; and let that King acknowledg God and ſeek him, as <hi>David</hi> did, and all his Enemies ſhall not prevail againſt him, but fall and periſh. <hi>David</hi> had a good Title, but a troubleſome Reign. 2. A good King when he takes a Kingdom, takes it not for the Glory and Eaſe of it, but for the Glory of God, and Good of his Kingdom, with all the Labours and Dangers of a War. 3. The true Intereſt, Peace and Happineſs of a Kingdom, is the Concernment of a good King. The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines had a great ſpight againſt <hi>David</hi>'s Perſon in the former Deſign and War, but now they hated <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which were the People of God, and profeſſed the true Religion, and now <hi>David</hi> is as much engaged to go out in Perſon againſt the Philiſtines. 4. A faithful and a valiant King will endure the great Toil and Wearineſs of a War, even to Faintneſs. 5. That even a <hi>David,</hi> a Servant of God, will find it a hard and hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Work to fight his Enemies. 6. A good and valiant King will expoſe his own Perſon, and tire himſelf in Battel, and yet not fly nor leave the Field; <hi>David</hi> waxed faint, but yet ſtands his ground. 7. The beſt and ſtouteſt King muſt feel his own Infirmities, that he may know that he conquereth not by his own Strength. 8. That though a good King ſhall prevail, yet firſt he may be brought very low and faint. The greateſt Champion will faint in time; and often-times a Cauſe and People may be brought very low before a Conqueſt. The Power of God will be ſeen in humane Weakneſs, and give him hot and fainting work, that his glorious Power may bring forth Victory and Peace.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Ver.</hi> 16. <hi>And</hi> Iſhbi-benob, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How exact an account have we here given us of this great Enemy of <hi>David?</hi> By his Name, a very notorious and noted Man, his Deſcent and Family, which was of the Sons of the Giant; his great Strength, his dangerous Weapon, <hi>The Weight of whoſe Spear weighed three hundred Shekels of Braſs in Weight;</hi>
               <note place="margin">About nine Pound ſix Ounces Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver depoiſe, <hi>Clark's</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. About half as big as <hi>Goliah</hi>'s, <hi>1</hi> Sam. <hi>17.7.</hi> but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to others a great deal more.</note> and by his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Preparation for Miſchief to <hi>David</hi>'s Perſon, <hi>being girded with a new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>word:</hi> Sword is not in the Original Text, but ſupplied for Explication, as contained in the word girded, <hi>Girded with a new</hi> —, ſomewhat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and fitted for his purpoſe to kill <hi>David.</hi> The judicious <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> doth conjecture, that he might be girded about in ſign of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made ſome Officer in the Army, and that he muſt do ſome great Action and meritorious Exploit, which became the greatneſs of his Family, and Strength, and the Dignity of his Place. This Story is brought in to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate the Danger and Deliverance of <hi>David,</hi> and to ſet forth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God in great Straits and Dangers, and to make God's People, and their Enemies alſo know, that let them have all the Advantages they can deſire, yet they ſhall not prevail againſt <hi>David</hi> and againſt <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Let us not go over ſo large a Text without making ſome Obſervations.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) You read <hi>David</hi>'s great Inequality and Diſadvantage: though when he was young he killed <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liah;</hi> but now <hi>David waxed faint:</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29877:7"/>of Strength and ſtature, what was <hi>David</hi> to him? but now here's <hi>David</hi> at a Diſadvantage, he <hi>waxed faint.</hi> There may be ſometimes great Diſproportions between the Servants of God, and the Enemies of God: The Servants of God may in Appearance be much the weaker.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The <hi>Aſſailant</hi> was a Man of note among the Philiſtines, a Man of Name, as <hi>Goliah</hi> was, from whom ſome great Action might be expected: The Enemies of God and his People may be furniſhed with Men extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily fitted, prepared, and reſolved, Men pick'd out for Deſigns and Attempts, pernicious to the People of God. Here was a great Man, a noted Man, a Man of great Strength and Stature, of deſperate Deſigns, for he thought of killing <hi>David;</hi> and yet when many Wagers might be laid on the Philiſtines Head and Party, it was ſo probable, if not ſure, that ſuch a Hand muſt needs prevail againſt <hi>David,</hi> yet <hi>David</hi> comes off ſafe, and his mortal Enemy falls and periſheth; the Giant had an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to attempt, and never was <hi>David</hi> in a worſe caſe to make his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and yet the Deſign failed. Such Men as theſe are not to be truſted to, if we had an Army of them on our ſide, nor to be feared;<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Jo. Mackenzie</hi>'s Narrat. of the Siege of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> p. <hi>2.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi> The new levied Souldiers were to be all near ſix Foot high, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable for their Bulk, whatever they were for their Courage.</note> though all our Enemies were ſuch, God can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat them all. Men cannot perform what Men would have them, or hope from them. How curious were our Enemies, the Philiſtines, in the choice of Regiments of great Stature and Strength? what confidence was put in them? and yet they proved but like Babes and Lub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bars.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) This <hi>Iſhbi-benob</hi> was girded with a new Sword, that is, as ſome conjecture, he was newly made ſome great Officer, from his being girded, a Mark of Honour; others, that his new Sword was a newly invented Weapon for his turn; and others think it might be a new Sword, not uſed before, the Edg of it was firſt to be tried upon <hi>David</hi>'s Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> How proud might this Man be of his Name, his Stature, his Strength, his Command, and his Sword? How often might he fancy <hi>David</hi>'s Head upon his Sword's Point,<note place="margin">See the Narrative of the French Joy for the Death of King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> in the Battel of <hi>Boyn.</hi>
               </note> and his Body at his Feet, and yet his Weapon ſhall not proſper againſt Good King <hi>David.</hi> Our Enemies the Philiſtines, have changed the way of fighting, invented new Inſtruments of War to make themſelves the more formidable; how may their ambitious, vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious <hi>Iſhbi-benobs</hi> boaſt what they will do with <hi>David?</hi> kill him, and then drag him in the Streets and Dunghils, and yet <hi>David</hi> is preſerved: Men and Weapons are alike vain and ineffectual, when God is a Shield to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">(4.) This <hi>Iſhbi-benob</hi> had <hi>David</hi> almoſt in his Power and within his reach, for <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſucccoured <hi>David,</hi> who <hi>waxed faint.</hi> Hence learn, the Enemy of <hi>David</hi> may be prepared to kill, may have a great Advantage over him, being weak and faint, and he had as fair and open Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29877:7"/>to make him think he had him as ſure as if he were in his Hand; and yet <hi>David</hi> eſcapes the Villain, tho a Giant. <hi>David</hi> was, and our <hi>David</hi> may be in great Danger, and nigh to Death, and yet preſerved: Great Dangers make great Deliverances, and the Deliverance is as ſure in great Danger, as in common and leſs. How near was <hi>David</hi> many a time to be cut off, yet he was delivered from the Hand of <hi>Saul, and all his Enemies;</hi> ſo we pray and truſt that God will be a Shield and a Succourer of our <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in all his Wars.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) He thought to have ſlain <hi>David,</hi> or he ſpake, as the word ſignifies, of killing <hi>David;</hi> perhaps by thinking of killing the King, he was am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious to have the Glory of winning the Field, and routing <hi>Iſrael,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to avenge the Philiſtines ſo often beaten and deſtroyed by <hi>David;</hi> his Spight and Aim was at <hi>David,</hi> not to take him, not to maim and hurt him, but outright to kill him: <hi>David</hi> had been ſucceſsful, and done great Services for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and for that the Philiſtines might hate him, and have particular Deſigns upon him. A victorious and a good King is hateful to Philiſtines. The greater Bleſſing a good King is to the <hi>Iſrael</hi> and Church of God, the more aimed at: but when his Dangers are greateſt, God is neareſt for his Salvation. <hi>David</hi> was aimed at, and he could not chooſe but know it, for they ſought him once before in particular, yet <hi>David</hi>'s Courage, Religion, Conſcience, and Care of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13.</note> did oblige him to go down to the Battel. <hi>David</hi> is faint, and when faint, the Enemy laid at him to have ſped him, and yet <hi>David</hi> is preſerved. It is extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary when God ſuiteth the Spirit of a King to his Charge and Dangers; and that King who turns not his back upon God's Cauſe, Religion, and People, may humbly expect that God will not turn his back upon him in his greateſt Dangers, but watch over him, and preſerve him. The King's wearing the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> makes the Philiſtines aim the more at his Head: His Greatneſs and Valour do multiply his Perils; but God who made him great for this Work, is mighty to ſave him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In <hi>ver.</hi> 17. we have theſe Remarkables. 1. A famous Act of <hi>Abiſhai the Son of</hi> Zeruiah <hi>who ſuccoured</hi> David, <hi>and he ſmote the Philiſtine, and killed him.</hi> 2. The Zeal and great Concern of the People for their King; <hi>Then the Men of</hi> David <hi>ſware unto him, ſaying, Thou ſhalt go no more out with us to Battel.</hi> 3. The Reaſon for that Reſolution and Zeal; <hi>That thou quench not the Light of</hi> Iſrael; that our Light and Glory may not be put out with thy Life, who art <hi>the Light of</hi> Iſrael. 4. <hi>David</hi>'s Permiſſion of that Oath and Reſolution of the People, and his Acquieſcence in that Act for his own and their Preſervation and Comfort.</p>
            <p>In the firſt of theſe we have many things to obſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt. Abiſhai</hi> the Son of <hi>Zeruiah;</hi> he was a valiant Man, and <hi>David</hi>'s Siſter's Son. Whence obſerve, It is under God and next to a Guard of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,<note place="margin">1 Chron 2.16.</note> a great Security for a King to have a Confident, and approved vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29877:8"/>truſty Friend at hand, in time and place of Danger; ſuch a Man was <hi>Abiſhai.</hi> How <hi>Abiſhai</hi> come now to be ſo near <hi>David</hi>'s Perſon, we do not know: whether he was there by Command as in his Place, or whether brought thither by the Providence of the Lord of Battel, there he was at hand for this eminent Service. Whence we will obſerve; 1. It is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God over <hi>David</hi> to place a valiant loyal Friend to ſuccour him in great Weakneſs and great Danger: So let us in all our <hi>David</hi>'s Danger, pray that God,<note place="margin">Exod. 15.3.</note> who is called a Man of War, and the Lord of Hoſts, would place an <hi>Abiſhai</hi> near his Perſon to ſuccour him in time of need. 2. It is a great Duty and Praiſe of a valiant loyal Captain, as <hi>Abiſhai</hi> was, to take care of the Perſon of a good and valiant King, and interpoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and Death or Harm. 3. <hi>Abiſhai</hi>'s care and buſineſs was not to carry <hi>David</hi> out of the Field, and to leave it with him, the great Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of Affection and Loyalty in many a Coward; but he ſtood by fainting <hi>David</hi> to ſuccour him in the Encounter, and to win the Day. This is true Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity both to the King and <hi>Iſrael</hi> alſo. 4. Whoever the Perſon be who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends <hi>David</hi> in a time of Danger, deſerves to be remembred and honoured for it; and it is an Honour to his Perſon and to his Houſe. Here <hi>David</hi>'s Second is named, <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> and his Family noted, <hi>Abiſhai the Son of Zerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> both remembred and honoured by this ſacred Penman: and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is not only done to a King's Perſon, but to the King's Kingdom. 5. Nay further, not only Men, but God himſelf takes notice of, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with Honour, that Perſon, or more, that ſuccour <hi>David</hi> when he is faint in fighting the Lord's Battels. And this ſhould be a great Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to all that are in chief Place, or near the Perſon of our King, to expoſe themſelves to ſight for the King's Preſervation: It is an Honour to their Name, an obliging Service to the King and <hi>Iſrael</hi> alſo; and they may do it with Succeſs upon the Enemy, and Safety to themſelves: and what can be more to embolden and inſpirit a Perſon to engage an Enemy? 6. The moſt valiant and ſtouteſt King may ſtand in need of Succour, and it's no diſhonour to the greateſt King to accept the Service; for he muſt know and acknowledg he cannot always hold out, nor conquer all with his own Hands. 7. That ſuch as come in to ſuccour a King in time of Danger, ſhould not hinder, nor be ſlack, nor make as though he did, but do his work effectually: <hi>Abiſhai</hi> did not make a ſhew, but effectually ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour'd him; this is a ſign of Courage, Skill and Fidelity. The Lord that provided one to ſuccour <hi>David</hi> at a hard puſh, deliver our King from trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Standers by and Cowards. This muſt be one of our Petitions for him, that either God would bind up the Hands of every villanous <hi>Iſhbi-benob,</hi> or ſend him ſome one or more to ſuccour him, as he did <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſmote the Philiſtine, and killed him. The Son of the Giant was over-tall, and too big for any ordinary Man to deal with; yet as big as he was, here is one that fears him not, but ſtrikes, and ſtrikes home
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29877:8"/>too, he ſmote and killed him: The Action is roundly expreſſed, he ſmote the Philiſtine and killed him. He was not long about him, but made ſhort work with him; he ſmote him and kill'd him. The Courage of <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> and his Skill and Vigor appear in the Stroak. But could <hi>Abiſhai</hi> come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his reach? Could not the Giant fence, and keep him off at Sword's point, and Arm's length? No, he could not it ſeems: he had bulk enough; a great maſs of Fleſh might hang upon his great Bones; he might have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true Courage nor Skill, but lay at catch to take <hi>David</hi> at an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of Weakneſs, and act the Coward's part. But now <hi>David</hi> is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, but ſuccoured; <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſtrikes once for all, and kills him. Look upon both theſe in their contrary Sides: The Son of the Giant is for the Philiſtines againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> really againſt God, and againſt his Church: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhai</hi> is <hi>David</hi>'s Officer and Servant, a Commander under him, as he was under God. From Particulars we muſt not conclude Univerſals. But God permits his Enemies now what he permitted then; yea, they have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many Men of great bulk and ſtature in one Kingdom, but like the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they are Fleſh and not Spirit; and in another, not raw and fleſhy Bodies without Courage, but diſciplin'd Armies and Veteranes: And they want not for new Swords, not for any Inventions and Furniture, for all Occaſions: ſuppoſe ſome excel in Bulk, in Fleſh and Bones, and yet want Skill and Courage for a noble and honourable Attempt; ſuppoſe others be Men expert in War, who excel in Skill, but want true Courage; ſuppoſe they exceed in Number, and are more than we are, but are ſuch as will not ſtand; ſhall we then only venture, and reckon according to Senſe and Reaſon? This is unworthy of the People of the mighty and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, who ſhould look by Faith upon him, and upon <hi>David</hi> though weak, yet in the Hand of God; and thus we ought to do. Then let us make ſuch Obſervations as theſe, to encourage our Faith and Hopes, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon God by Prayer. 1. There are none ſo great, ſo ſtrong, ſo big in the Enemies Army, but God can find out Men to fetch them down. The Philiſtines had an <hi>Iſhbi-benob,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> had an <hi>Abiſhai</hi> on his ſide, who proved too hard for him. 2. When the Enemies of <hi>David</hi> exceed in Stature, Strength and Arms, it makes them but the more bold to venture and deſign what will prove to their own Deſtruction. The Philiſtines were appointed for deſtruction; and when they thought themſelves fit for War, they were fit for Deſtruction. They made many Wars againſt <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and before <hi>David</hi> appeared, but never had ſucceſs, but when the Sins of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were ripe for Puniſhment. Our Enemies are as like them as if they were deſcended from them; how Philiſtine-like did they uſe <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</hi> The Inhumanities of our Enemies are a reproach to Nature, of which they have as little, as they have of Grace and true Religion. Our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are given to burn and make deſolate; they cannot reſt from troubling <hi>David,</hi> raiſing War after War: and what but Bitterneſs in the latter end,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29877:9"/>is, and will be the Fruit of their Wars and Commotions? Their very Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants are for the Slaughter; becauſe every Battel againſt them is the Lord's, therefore they cannot ſtand. 3. A great, a bold, a daring Enemy of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> is as ſoon killed as the weakeſt; what could be ſooner done? And <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſmote the Philiſtine and kill'd him; and what became of his ſtrong and his mighty Arm, or his new Sword then? 4. The Enemies of God, and his <hi>David,</hi> may imagine and deſign greateſt miſchief to him, but are ſo far from being able to execute and perform their Counſels and Deſigns, that they periſh in the attempt to execute them. 5. The Servants of God and the King ſhould not fear a Philiſtine, tho he were an armed Giant, in the defence of the King and <hi>Iſrael:</hi> let him ſmite, and kill at once. 6. It is a Duty, and a neceſſary part of Wiſdom to know when, and whom the Servants of God muſt ſmite and ſpare, or ſmite and kill: <hi>Abiſhai</hi> was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at it, and <hi>David</hi> was not ſo faint but he might have bad him forbear to kill, if it had not been his Duty. There is a great difference to be made between ſome Enemies and others. 7. The Inſtruments of God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon his Enemies, do quickly and effectually execute his Pleaſure upon them; <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſmote and killed him. 8. How dreadful is it for any Man to be an Enemy to God, and his People <hi>Iſrael?</hi> It muſt needs be a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be diſappointed of his Aim, had <hi>David</hi> only eſcaped his and been preſerved, and he eſcaped and fled? To loſe the pleaſure of his Enmity againſt him, to loſe the honour of ſuch a Fact, and the prey and reward of his Service; but not only to fail, but to periſh, and go down to Hell in a moment, what Horror attends his Breath going out of his Noſtrils! What a tormenting Diſappointment was it to miſs of <hi>David,</hi> and die in a doing Enterprize?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Another thing in the Words is the zealous Action and Behaviour of the People, and the uſe they made of the King's Deliverance: Then the Men of <hi>David ſware unto</hi> him, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt go no more with us to Battel.</hi> They had in another caſe withſtood the King's Declaration to them of going in perſon with his Army into the Field againſt <hi>Abſalom.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3.</note> There they did more than humbly diſſwade the King from going; they did reſolutely gainſay the King's Declaration; but the People anſwered; <hi>Thou ſhalt not go forth;</hi> and gave their reaſon for it: But here they carry their Reſolution higher; they ſwore unto the King, <hi>thou ſhalt go no more to Battel,</hi> &amp;c. What would ſome of our late Aſſerters and Promoters of the Abſolute Power of Kings have ſaid of this Caſe? The Perſons were all <hi>David</hi>'s Subjects, and yet they ſware <hi>unto the King;</hi> they ſware unto the King without asking his leave or licenſe; they ſware unto the King, not to bind themſelves to their Duty to him, but to bind him, and to bind him abſolutely, without limitation or reſtriction, <hi>Thou ſhalt go no more out with us to Battel.</hi> Tho their Concernment for the King and Kingdom's Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Welfare was good, yet thus it would have been interpreted. 1.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29877:9"/>To reſtrain the King from going out to Battel any more. 2. And for them to ſwear that he ſhould not go, was to exerciſe an Act of Superiority and Uſurpation over the King's Power and Liberty. 3. And tho the End and Intention was good to preſerve the King's Life, and the Light of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> yet was it not doing ill that good might come of it? 4. Was it not ill done of <hi>David</hi> the King to ſuffer ſuch an Oath to be made, and an embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Subjects to combine and to ſwear, obtaining this, to have what they liſt at any time? Was it not a defect in <hi>David</hi>'s Government, to ſuffer this, and to be impoſed upon? I ſhall not enter into Enquiries on this Subject; but it is neceſſary to ſay ſomething to the matter. The Judgment of <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> a Reformer of great Learning, Judgment and Sincerity, is much to be valued: Saith be,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Comment. in</hi> 2 Sam. 21.17.</note> 
               <q>The Men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did piouſly think, that the King ſhould not be expoſed to danger. As the Members are willing to be endangered for the Head, ſo it is the duty of good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to take care of the Safety of their Princes —. And, ſaith he, it is not unbecoming Kings,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> chap. 18</note> ſometimes to yield to the honeſt Counſels of their Subjects.—</q>
            </p>
            <p>That which is obvious will keep us from falling into Briars in the dark. 1. It is certain that <hi>David</hi> was a Sovereign King in his Kingdom. 2. His Government was by God's Inſtitution and Appointment. 3. King and People were ſo united for the moſt part, that they agreed in one common Deſign and End, the Publick Good, here called the Light of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The People did highly and juſtly honour and eſteem the King,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3.</note> and the King did ſincerely regard their Proſperity and Happineſs. 4. The People were not a Generation of brutiſh Animals, nor ſo deſpiſed; they know wherein the Happineſs of their Kingdom did conſiſt, and made bold to do more than petition, they gainſaid the King's Will, in conſcience of his and the common Safety. 5. The King did not oppoſe his Will againſt their Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and free Reſolutions neither; but underſtanding their Will, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended to it; and without diſputing Prerogative, did acquieſce and yield. 6. The People did highly value the King's Life above their own; they would continue in their Loyalty to the King and Kingdom, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the Hazards of War in their Perſons, and go to War, but provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for his Safety, and the Safety of the Kingdom in his. 7. The Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Senſe of publick Dangers and publick Safety, and their expreſſing and declaring that Senſe, is not inconſiſtent with their ſtricteſt Duty, nor higheſt Honour towards a Sovereign King of God's own Deſignation: And Self-denial for publick Benefit is no derogation from ſoveraign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. 8. The nature of their Oath was high and ſtrict, as if they had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſo far to diſpoſe of the King's Perſon, as to bind him for his and the Kingdom's undoubted Good and Welfare: they ſware unto the King, that he ſhould go no more out with them to Battel; but they add their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29877:10"/>Reaſon, <hi>That thou quench not the Light of Iſrael.</hi> So much of the Peoples Act.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> The reaſon of their Oath to the King contains very excellent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which being duly applied, will be a means to continue to us the Light of our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A good, holy, righteous King and Governour is given of God in Mercy to a People, to be to them <hi>a great, publick Bleſſing.</hi> As the Sun is a Light to the World, ſo is a good King to a Kingdom. And this is the difference between a King of God's Donation and Appointment, and a King by a judicial Permiſſion, to a diſſatisfied, diſcontented People. The deſire of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> was after a King,<note place="margin">1 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.20. &amp; 8.5, 19.</note> and they had one granted them; but what he proved, need not here be repeated; but as bad as he was, he was true to the common Intereſt of the Kingdom, againſt the Enemies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and went not about to ſubject it to foreign Powers. When he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, God provided him a King,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.1.</note> as he told <hi>Samuel;</hi> and he whom God provided in Mercy, was a Light to <hi>Iſrael:</hi> God's Favour did ſhine upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> through <hi>David</hi> their King. God hath as full a right to reject a King in our days as ever he had, and to provide a King; and that King whom God provides, a wiſe People will highly eſteem: and God may juſtly be diſpleaſed at thoſe, who are not pleaſed with what God provides. Do not they forget God's unlimited Soveraignty over all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World, who aſſert the abſolute Power of Kings in their own Dominions, to ſet up and caſt down, without reſpect to Juſtice or Mercy? But the God of the whole Earth hath in Juſtice driven away one, and brought in another: Greateſt Mercy! and ſhall we mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur at our Mercy?</p>
            <p n="2">2. That as a good King is an eminent, ſhining publick Bleſſing, like the Light of the Sun; ſo it is the duty and wiſdom of a People to eſteem and honour him, as the great Gift of God: So the Men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did behold <hi>David</hi> as the Light of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> they knew what a publick Benefit they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from him: they remembred the evil Days of <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> (out of which <hi>David</hi> in his Lamentation for him pick'd the beſt) in compariſon of which the Days of <hi>David</hi> were like Light compared to Darkneſs and Tempeſt. But when a People ſhall be weary of Light, or murmur againſt it, or be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied with it, and ſhall wiſh for Darkneſs, Hail and Thunder, Blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Mildew, they ſin againſt their Temporal State, as they do againſt their Spiritual, by loving Darkneſs rather than Light; and without any fanciful Alluſion, but in real Truth, they hate the Light becauſe their Deeds are evil, and leſt they ſhould be reproved, and be obliged to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Happineſs of a Kingdom doth much depend upon the Life and Preſervation of a good King; <hi>Leſt thou quench the Light of Iſrael;</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29877:10"/>not only the Light and Glory of his own Family, and the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> but the Light of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> that the Light of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and not of <hi>Judah</hi> or <hi>Bethlehem</hi> only, or any part of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but all <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Their Light of Proſperity, Peace and Glory, was bound up in the Bundle of his Life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A People that are ſenſible of their Happineſs, and the Benefit of the Preſervation of a good King, will do all they can to preſerve it. The Men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were ſenſible of the Advantage and Bleſſing of a good King, and foreſaw the loſs that would befal them by his Death. They valued him highly, and yet really below his worth when they ſaid,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3, 4.</note> He <hi>was worth ten thouſand of them;</hi> it had been a greater loſs to have loſt <hi>David,</hi> than ten thouſand of the People. They value him according to his Worth, when they admire and honour him as the very Light of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and therefore they do with all humility and earneſtneſs, oblige him to keep out of the reach of the Enemies Sword; they will fight if he will keep himſelf ſafe at Home; we will go out to Battel, but thou ſhalt not go with us.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Yet obſerve the reach of the Argument and Reaſon, <hi>That thou quench not the Light of Iſrael.</hi> A good King, being a great and publick Bleſſing to his Kingdom, ſhould not expoſe himſelf to unneceſſary Dangers, but take care to preſerve himſelf, for the Kingdom's ſake and Benefit. A clear Evidence that good Kings are not their own but their Kingdom's. The Argument is drawn from his own Safety and Danger, and from their loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Affection to him; but the Argument reacheth further, to the common and publick Danger, if he hazard himſelf, and the common and publick Benefit of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of the whole Kingdom; <hi>that thou quench not thine own Light, but ours alſo.</hi> The Light of a King is for the Kingdom's Good.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A King is, and a good King will reckon himſelf to be as much for his People, the Publick and Univerſal Good, as the People can be for him. Here they intimate, that they will go to Battel when there is cauſe, and more they cannot venture, more they cannot do than ſerve the King with their Eſtates and Lives; but then, if he be as the Light of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he ſhould take care of himſelf, with reſpect to them and their Benefit. His Light is their Light, and he ſhould be as careful of theirs as of his own. When it is well with the one, it is well with the other.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Yet again, mark the words, they do not ſay, That the Light of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> be not quenched, but, <hi>That thou quench not the Light of</hi> Iſrael. This Reaſon grows out of the Sides of the former, that a King receiving his Authority and Gifts from God, under God, for his Peoples Profit and Welfare, ſhould imploy all his Abilities for their Proſperity, he ſhould communicate and ſend forth all his Abilities and Powers, (as the Sun dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth his Influences upon inferior Bodies) to make his People happy in him: So on the contrary, he ſhould be exceeding tender of doing any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29877:11"/>thing that ſhould be to their detriment; and eſpecially that he by going to Battel, ſhould die, that he quench not their Light; it would be his own Act, that would be fatal to himſelf and them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly.</hi> The laſt Particular in the Verſe is, the King's Acquieſcence and tacit Conceſſion and Permiſſion of their Oath taken out of ſincere Loyalty and Affection to the King's Preſervation, and their own in him. In God's Kingdom, and in a godly King's Reign, the People might lawfully, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rebuke, loyally admoniſh the King of the common Danger, and more than petition, even ſwear, that he ſhould not go forth to Battel, that the Light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> be not quenched. <hi>David</hi> was a Wiſe, Holy, Religious, and Heroick Prince; a King of long Experience and great Valour; it was hard for him to refrain from a Battel, altho he fainted: But doth the Publick Happineſs, Glory and Proſperity, depend upon it? Doth it ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Publick? Do the Men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> remonſtrate, intreat, and ſwear alſo? then he takes himſelf to be obliged to condeſcend and acquieſce. I am perſwaded this Doctrine was true in thoſe ancient and pureſt Times. This was not a Surprize upon <hi>David,</hi> or a Thing inconſiderately conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to, but what he yielded to once before in <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Rebellion. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that <hi>David</hi> had commanded and ordered his Army into three Bodies, under three Generals, and given them Orders, he declared he would go forth with them:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>And the King ſaid unto the People, I will ſurely go forth with you my ſelf alſo. But the People anſwered, Thou ſhalt not go forth: for if we flee away, they will not care for us; neither if half of us die, will they care for us: but thou art worth ten thouſand of us; therefore it is better that thou ſuccour us out of the City. And the King ſaid unto them, What ſeemeth you beſt, I will do.</hi> Here was ſecret Policy, and ſound Reaſon, on both Sides. <hi>David</hi> had ſtill a tender Affection, if not a ſecret Fondneſs for <hi>Abſalom.</hi> O how did his Affections open towards him! He gave Charge to his three Generals, in the hearing of all the People, <hi>Deal gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my ſake with the young Man, even with</hi> Abſalom: Every Word hath an Argument to oblige them to deal gently with <hi>Abſalom.</hi> O how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly did he take on for his Death; O Abſalom, <hi>my Son, my Son; would God I had died for thee:</hi> He loved him better than his Life; but in being ruled by his Peoples plain Advice, he ſhewed he loved <hi>Iſrael</hi> better than <hi>Abſalom.</hi> And the Reaſon which lay concealed was, that he might take care to ſave <hi>Abſalom</hi> alive. He ſaid he would go, but gave no Reaſon for his Reſolution; it was ſufficient for him to declare his Reſolution, <hi>I will ſurely go forth with you my ſelf alſo,</hi> as he was wont to do.</p>
            <p>On the Peoples part, there was great Reaſon and Policy not pleaſing to the King, for they had an Eye upon <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and to put an End to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, by putting an End to his Life if he fell into their Hands. The ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Reaſons were built upon good Principles: And if <hi>David</hi> did ſmell their ſecret Reaſons againſt <hi>Abſalom,</hi> his ſelf-denial for the Peoples Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29877:11"/>was exceeding exemplary. If any ſay, that it was weakly done of <hi>David,</hi> to grant ſo much to the People againſt his own Will; take notice, that this did not proceed from <hi>David</hi>'s weakneſs and overſight; it was not from Error in Government, for <hi>David</hi> was under no eclipſe of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, for he was able to diſpoſe and order his Affairs; he took a Muſter of his Army, <hi>and ſet Captains of Thouſands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 18.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>and Captains of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds over them; and</hi> David <hi>ſent forth a third part of his Army under</hi> Joab, <hi>and a third part of his Army under the hand of</hi> Abiſhai <hi>the Son of</hi> Zeruiah, Joab<hi>'s Brother, and a third part under the hand of</hi> Ittai <hi>the Gittite.</hi> As he could Marſhal an Army, ſo it ſeems he could hearken to Reaſon; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Reaſon; comply with the Deſires of his People, in the fulleſt terms of Reſpect to their Counſel; <hi>What ſeemeth you beſt, I will do.</hi> The Will of both Parties was pleaſing to God,<note place="margin">Tam enim David quàm popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus iſtâ in re non ſua quaerebat, &amp;c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde apparet non eſſe indeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ut Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do boneſtis ſubditorum Conſiliis pareant. In <hi>1 Sam. 18.</hi>
               </note> ſaith the Judicious <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> for it proceeded from Love: the King and the People ſought not their own private Things, or factious Deſigns; the Souldiers did not reſiſt their King out of Impudence, but Reverence and Love. Happy is the Kingdom, when King and People aim at the ſame Publick Good, and jointly move upon Principles of mutual Affection and Safety: And when both are ſincerely One in their Deſigns and Aims, and have a mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in one another. When Kings can do all themſelves in War and Peace, then let them be abſolute; but till then, the Reaſons of a People, for the King's Honour and Safety, and Peace of the Kingdom, by putting an End to Wars and quietting Inſurrections, are not to be deſpiſed, but approved of by the wiſeſt and the greateſt Kings; and People ſhould be ſo wiſe and dutiful as to offer nothing but what ſhould carry Weight and Conviction, that they do really wiſh well to their King; and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of a King to be overcome by the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their People. Publick Reaſon ſhould prevail againſt private Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in publick Perſons. As <hi>David</hi> was over-ruled, without uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People upon his Soveraignty, at that time, ſo now, though the People ſwore to him that he ſhould not go forth to Battel for fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kill'd, to the Nation's loſs, ſo he did not reject them, nor ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf diſpleaſed with them. He did not miſunderſtand them, nor check and threaten them; he did not ſend forth his Proclamation or Declaration againſt them, or confine and impriſon the Heads of them. They ſpake their Love, and he ſaw it; though they ſwear he ſhould not go out and endanger Himſelf and the State, he did not make them an Example by Puniſhment or Revenge for medling with his Prerogative. His Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations were towards the Wars, and his Valour was not extinct, though his Strength abated; and yet he would not inſiſt upon his own Soveraign Power, nor take a high Action to reſtrain it, to be an encroachment upon it. Sincere Loyalty will make a People bold for their Prince's ſafety. Wiſe Kings love to ſee the Love and Loyalty of their People, and will
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29877:12"/>rather unhend their own Inclinations, than break with their honeſt well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning Subjects.</p>
            <p>I will conclude with this one Obſervation; He was a wiſe and holy King, worthy the Imitation of the greateſt, who was for the Kingdom's Good, ruled againſt his own Inclination. It was then when <hi>Salus publica,</hi> the publick Safety, was the ſupream Law. It was when People thought the King to be themſelves, and when the King thought the People to be himſelf: The People thought, ſave the King, and we ſave our ſelves; and when he thought, I will ſave my ſelf, to ſave the People: It was when a People underſtood their own Good, and ſought it with one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and when the King conſented to it, when one Light was the Light of both.</p>
            <p>I have gone over the Words, and made too many Obſervations to be diſcourſed on.</p>
            <p>I deſire now further, that you would more particularly obſerve two Points.</p>
            <p n="1">I. A good King is the Light of a Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">II. A People ſhould be ſenſible of the great Bleſſing of a good King, and ſhould be much concerned, and very zealous for his and their own Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p n="1">I. A good King is the Light of a Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Light, that is, the Glory and Cauſe of Proſperity to a Kingdom, ſo is the Light of Heaven to the World: Light is the Glory of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the firſt-born, the Excellency and Dignity of the Creatures: How do the benign Influences of the Light make the Earth to flouriſh? How proſperous was <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the Light of <hi>David!</hi> The Dread and Horror of the Night is driven away at the Appearance of the Light; the Beaſts of Prey run to their Dens, the Terror and Devourers of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God are forced to hide their Heads: Perſecutors are afraid to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or moleſt the little Flock: the Works of Darkneſs and of the Night dare not with an impudent Faoe be publiſhed; Chambring and Wantonneſs,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.13. 1 Theſſ. 5.4, 6.</note> Rioting and Drunkenneſs, nor Strife and Envy. The Light of a holy Magiſtrate gives no Countenance to ſhameful Practices. The Majeſty and Glory of God ſhines in the Light of a bleſſed King: and as God is Light, ſo he who is the Image of that Light, ſhines for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and God ſhines for the Glory of his People: <hi>The Light of the Wicked ſhall be put out, and the Spark of his Fire ſhall not ſhine. The Light ſhall be dark in his Tabernacle, and his Candle ſhall be put out with him,</hi> Job. 18.5, 6. <hi>i. e.</hi> his Honour and Glory ſhall be put out; his Proſperity ſhall fade away and die.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A good King is a good ſign that God will not deſtroy the Kingdom; 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.19. <hi>Yet the Lord would not deſtroy</hi> Judah, <hi>for</hi> David <hi>his Servant's ſake, as he promiſed him to give him always a Light, and to his Children:</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:29877:12"/>therefore God would not deſtroy <hi>Judah,</hi> becauſe he had promiſed <hi>David</hi> to give him a Light, that is, a Succeſſor in his Throne, to give Light to his People: therefore the giving of that Light, was a Preſervation to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> from Deſtruction. When God was provoked by <hi>Solomon,</hi> who threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him for his Idolatry and Breach of Covenant, to rend the Kingdom from him, and give it unto his Servant; he was pleaſed to add, How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I will not do it in thy Days for <hi>David</hi> thy Father's ſake, but I will rend it out of the Hand of thy Son: He would not for <hi>David</hi>'s ſake, to whom God promiſed a Lampalways; 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.4. <hi>Nevertheleſs, for</hi> David<hi>'s ſake did the Lord his God give him a Lamp in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to ſet up his Son, and to eſtabliſh</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A good King is Light to a Kingdom, as he is a cauſe of Joy and Gladneſs to a Kingdom. A bad King may cauſe carnal and profane Joy to the Wicked, but then he is the Cauſe and Grief and Trouble to them that fear God We are not to call that Light which makes the Wicked to rejoice in their Wickedneſs, and to glory in their Shame: but then we have a Light when the Righteous rejoice: <hi>Whon the Righteous are in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the People rejoice; but when the Wicked beareth Rule, the People mourn,</hi> Prov. 29.2. Light is borrowed to expreſs Joy and Gladneſs: <hi>Light is ſown for the Righteous, and Gladneſs for the upright in Heart,</hi> Pſal. 97.11. <hi>Then had the Jews Light and Gladneſs, and Joy and Honour,</hi> Eſther 8.16. What a Conſtellation of Bleſſings, what Cluſters of Mercies, and all in the Flower, ariſe and ſpring up in a Land, when ſuch a Light is ſet up in the Firmament of a Kingdom, in the Orb of Soveraignty!</p>
            <p n="4">4. A good King is the Light and Glory of a Kingdom, the Light of a People, when he doth reſtore, ſet up, reſorm and maintain Religion in his Kingdom; ſuch a King was <hi>David,</hi> ſuch a Bleſſing was he to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> When the Ark of God was taken, the miſerable ſorrowful Wife of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> called her Child's Name <hi>Ichabod,</hi> becauſe the Glory was departed from <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and ſhe ſaid, <hi>The Glory is departed from</hi> Iſrael; <hi>for the Ark of God is taken,</hi> 1 Sam. 4.21, 22. <hi>Surely Salvation is nigh them that fear him, that Glory may dwell in our Land,</hi> Pſal. 85.9. Chriſt is called, <hi>A Light to the Gentiles, and the Glory of his People</hi> Iſrael, Luke 2.32. Therefore then it is that Glory dwells in the Land, when the Glory of Chriſt ſhines in his Worſhip, Ordinances, and People: The Glory and Liberty of the Goſpel in its Miniſtry, Ordinances, and Profeſſion of its Truth and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Holineſs, doth exalt a Nation, advanceth it in great Honour; and then Glory doth not come as a Traveller to ſee a Country, or a way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring Man that tarrieth for a Night, but dwelleth in a Land: when Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, pure and undeſiled, is entertained with Reverence and Honour in the King's Court, in the Houſes of Nobles, and hath a free Paſſage throughout a Nation, and is delivered from unreaſonable Men: A religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King is then the Light of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> when the Lights of the World are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29877:13"/>ſet up, kept burning, brought from under Buſhels, and ſet upon the Table, when good Men may be as good as they will, and the wicked may not be as vile and bad as they would be.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A good King is a Light to a Kingdom when he reigns in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>David</hi>'s Prayer for <hi>Solomon</hi> was,<note place="margin">Pſal. 72.2.</note> 
               <hi>Give the King thy Judgments, and thy Righteouſneſs to the King's Son:</hi> This was his Prayer for him who was a Lamp which God promiſed to raiſe up in his place: and when a King doth reign in Righteouſneſs, then he imitates and repreſents the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſ, Chriſt Jeſus the King, the Scepter of whoſe Kingdom is a Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Righteouſneſs,<note place="margin">Mal. 4.2. 2 Sam. 23.3, 4.</note> who ariſeth <hi>with healing in his Wings. The God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſaid, the Rock of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſpake to me, He that ruleth over Men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God.</hi> Now mark what a juſt King, a religious King, that ruleth in the Fear of the Lord, ſhall be: <hi>And he ſhall be as the Light of the Morning, when the Sun riſeth, even a Morning without Clouds, as the tender Graſs ſpringeth out of the Earth by clear ſhining after Rain;</hi> i. e. he ſhall be a great Bleſſing, a great Comfort and Cauſe of rejoicing to the People of God. A King that reigns in Righteouſneſs may yet further be compared to the Light, as he doth by himſelf, by his righteous Laws de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and enact what is juſt and right, that by the Light of his Laws People may ſee the Light of the Rule, and the Path of Righteouſneſs; that by his wiſe, learned and upright Judges (not to ſerve the Deſigns, Will, and ſinful Pleaſure of the King, with a Commiſſion during Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to take away the Lives of innocent Men, to countenance falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, perplex or threaten the True, diſannul Charters, and the like) <hi>Righteouſneſs may run down like a mighty ſtream:</hi> When theſe do diſtribute Juſtice between the King and his People, and Subject and Subject; when the Righteous will not be ſold for a pair of Shoes; when Righteouſneſs is adminiſtred without Partiality, then the King will find the Benefit and Comfort of his own Light, for Righteouſneſs and Judgment will be the Stability or Eſtabliſhment of his Throne; <hi>For by Righteouſneſs the Throne is eſtabliſhed,</hi> Prov. 16.12.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The King is a Light to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> was for the Security and Protection received from him: The Sun and Shield are well joined for the Comfort and Protection of God's People, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. The Shields of the Earth belong unto the Lord;<note place="margin">Pſal. 47.7.</note> Kings and Magiſtrates are thoſe Shields, and they are Nurſing-Fathers and Nurſing-Mothers; they are like a Pillar of Fire for the Direction and Protection of <hi>Iſrael. Hezekiah</hi> in the Type of Jeſus Chriſt, was foretold, that he ſhould be a King to reign in Righteouſneſs, and the Princes under him ſhould rule in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; when it was ſo, it followeth, that he ſhould <hi>be a hiding-place from the Wind, and a Covert from the Tempeſt;</hi> a hiding-place and Covert from the Wind and Tempeſt raiſed by the Devil and his Angels, to trouble and unſettle the Nation's Peace and Order, and to keep off the Wind and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29877:13"/>Tempeſt, Perſecution and Tribulation, which blow and beat upon the Church of God; ſuch a Light was <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> A Man may follow his Trade, travel, and be commonly very ſafe, if he walk by Day, for Day-light is a Defence unto him.</p>
            <p>In theſe Inſtances you have heard the Benefit of a good King, as he is the Light of a Kingdom. Now, hearken a little further, and you ſhall ſee what cauſe a People have to honour and ſtudy the Happineſs of ſuch a King, and their own in him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As the Light is immediately from God, ſo is a holy, religious, wiſe and valiant King, as <hi>David</hi> was, a peculiar Creature of that glorious Maker, (and not a meer humane Creature, as all that are conſtituted by Men) and a peculiar Bleſſing and Treaſure to a People: that Fitneſs for Government which is in him, the placing of him in his Throne, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of him from one part of his Sphere to another, is a Remove made by the ſpecial Providence of God. God alone doth make the Light, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares and qualifies a King for Government; and the more of Providence appears, the greater is the Mercy to a People.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the Light is above the Earth, for the benefit of things below him, ſo is a King placed in a Degree of Sublimity above his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but altogether for <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Good. A King is above, but for his Subjects. And as the Light of Heaven is placed in Heaven, for the good of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures underneath; ſo are Kings placed by God in high Places, that their Vertues may deſcend upon their Inferiors.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the Light ſhines from above, and ſends and ſpreads forth its Powers and Influences afar off to all the Corners of the Earth; ſo a good King doth not reſtrain, but takes Pleaſure in communicating his Goodneſs to all the parts of his Dominions: He hath his Vehicles, Means and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, to convey the Stores of Gifts and Abilities for Good, which God hath enriched him with. All People that do not forfeit, ſhould be the better for him, and ſo all his Subjects ſhould know how much the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they are for him; the Riches of a King's Abilities are beyond all the Riches we entruſt him with for our Peace and Safety.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But notwithſtanding theſe great Advantages the King had of doing Good, and the People received from his diffuſive Goodneſs, <hi>yet he is liable to Mortality;</hi> the Light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> may be quench'd: he is a Light, but ſuch a Light as may be put out and quenched.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Iſrael</hi> was, ſo all People ſhould be ſenſible of the publick Bleſſing and Good received from a King who is as the Light of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſhould be much concerned and zealous for his Preſervation as their own.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You cannot but feel by reading the Words, the true ſenſe which the Men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had of their Happineſs in <hi>David,</hi> he was a great Light to them, communicating and ſtreaming down the Effects of his Light upon them: They remembred the Night out of which they came, the Trouble
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29877:14"/>and Confuſion, the Dangers and Injuries, the Diſhonours and Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which kept them in fears ſo long; they conſidered the happy change in Affairs, what a new Face the Light had given; and not a Face of Affairs only, but a ſtrong Conſtitution of the Body of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and they foreſaw what a Night would follow upon his Fall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They were much concerned and zealous for his Preſervation; he had eſcaped the Dangers of many Battels, and ſo might do again; his Strength failed, but he was able for Conduct; he was near to be ſlain by a reſolute, maſty, deſperate Giant, who thought to kill him, but he was ſuccoured ſeaſonably, and with Succeſs; and if ever h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould come out to Battel again, they would all be ready to defend his Perſon. Why might not he as long as he was able to endure the Fatigue with any Spirit, go out to Battel? Would not his Conduct and his Preſence direct and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate them, and ſo further the War towards a proſperous Iſſue? None of theſe Suggeſtions, nor many more could abate their Care, nothing but this, to keep himſelf ſafe in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the City of the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They were ſo much concerned and ſo zealous for his Preſervation, as if all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould fall with him, if he ſhould fall in Battel; <hi>That thou quench not the Light of</hi> Iſrael; as if all the Light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did ſhine from him, and were all of it comprehended in him, as the Lamp that gave Light to all the Branches: As if the Sun ſhould be put out, the Moon and Stars would be extinguiſhed. If the Pillars of a State or Kingdom fall, the Kingdom muſt needs come down, and fall to Ruin and Confuſion: but if the Supporter of theſe Pillars fall, the Pillars muſt fall, and all that ſtand upon them, and are ſupported by them: Now, ſaid <hi>David, The Earth and all the Inhabitants thereof are diſſolved, I bear up the Pillars of it,</hi> Pſal. 75.3. The Earth, that is <hi>Judea,</hi> and all the Inhabitants thereof are diſſolved, are unlinked, the Land lieth waſte, and like a Wilderneſs, and the Inhabitants thereof are unbound and untied; they are jealous and afraid of one another, being diſſolved into Factions and Parties; ſome Pillars there are,<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.3.</note> and I bear them up. <hi>If the Foundations be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,</hi> (if Towns, Magiſtrates, and Government, and Order be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed) <hi>what ſhall the Righteous do?</hi> they ſhall be made a Prey? What can we that are but few in Number, and weak in Power, do? What can we do if the Foundations be deſtroyed, till the Foundations of Religion, Righteouſneſs and Peace are laid? Bleſſed <hi>David</hi> was like the Light in Heaven on high, and like the Foundation beneath, that bears up the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars which bear the Houſe. If the Light be quenched, there follows Darkneſs and all the Confuſions and Miſeries of Darkneſs; if the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations be diſſolved, what but Ruine? Wo then to the Land, if its Light and Glory paſs away, as of Neceſſity it will, if thou put out the Light of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> All ſtands and all falls together; for if <hi>David</hi> be the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> the Houſe, if the Foundation fall, the Houſe will tumble,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29877:14"/>and of a well-ordered Fabrick, it will tumble into Heaps. <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> the Glory of all Lands, are but one united Light; and he is the Sun in the Firmament; if he be quenched, our Glory will depart. Thus were they concerned for themſelves in <hi>David</hi> their King: And how could any People in the World expreſs more care and zeal towards him, than they did in ſo few words? 1. They unanimouſly conſent to prevail with him to keep himſelf as choicely as might be, as you would keep in a Lamp or Light growing low in the Socket of expiring Age. 2. They ſwear to him that he ſhall not go out to Battel. 3. They tell him there will be no need of his going, for they will go to Battel, as willingly as if he were with them. 4. Surely <hi>David</hi> who had been their Light, would not be acceſſary to, or guilty of ſo great a Miſchief, as to put out their Light; they preſume up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it that he would not do ſuch an Act: Would he be ſuch an Enemy unto them now, as to turn their Day into Night? Surely no; therefore they oblige him not to expoſe himſelf; for if Evil ſhould befal him, Evil would befal them, and they ſhould impute it to him: it would be the worſt of Acts, and it would be his own: he felt the Zeal of a loyal People, which melted him into a compliance with their Deſires.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>APPLICATION.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This is not a Day to diſſemble, nor ſlatter God nor Man. I ſhall ſpeak nothing in the Uſe, but according to the Truth, in the Doctrines raiſed from this Text: I ſhall ſpeak becauſe I do believe, and nothing but what I believe: I ſpeak my Judgment and my Conſcience, and therefore I will ſpeak freely and boldly: I would not be deceived nor miſinformed my ſelf, nor would I miſlead you into any Error, nor now forbear to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you in Duty, in a great Duty, in a needful time.</p>
               <p>Was <hi>David</hi> a Light to <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Did <hi>Iſrael</hi> account him ſo? Were they tender of him? Were they concerned and zealous for him, as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Bleſſing of their Age and Nation? O what cauſe have we to bleſs God for that ſingular Bleſſing God hath beſtowed upon us of theſe Nations in our King and Queen, who are both but one great reſplendent Light of our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Give me leave to ſpeak freely, for your Profit and Information. 1. As they are both Lights. 2. As they are both joined in one Light. 3. As they are both our Light, the Light of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As they are both Light, and as they are both one Light; one in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of Judgment and Affection, one in conſort of Government. Are they not both Light by Illumination in the ſame Faith and Religion? Are they not Light for Wiſdom and Knowledg, able to direct and order the great and manifold Affairs of Government, both Military and Civil? Are they not Light, by the conſpicuity of their eminent Qualities and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Are they not Light, diffuſing the bleſſed Influences of their Royal Goodneſs and Authority to all the Corners of their Dominions? Who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29877:15"/>but obſtinate Rebels, or ſullen Male-contents, will not acknowledg this? And was more Clemency ever ſhewed towards open Rebels, or offered and declared to Murmurers, than by our gracious King and Queen? Let diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected Perſons ſpeak like Men of Senſe and Reaſon, much more like Men of Conſcience, and they muſt by ſpeaking Truth reprove their own Murmuring and Diſcontents. Are they not Lights, who have ſet up Stars and Angels, burning Lights in the Church, and reſtored them to light, who for many years were under Clouds, and the lowring Aſpect of the Rulers of the Kingdom, and given them liberty to take their ſeveral Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks, to give out their Light, and ſpend their Oil? Is it not by their Light, that Popiſh and Antichriſtian Darkneſs, and thick Darkneſs is fled away, or conſtrained to keep up cloſe, not in Holes and Caverns of the Earth, nor into Priſons and Dungeons indeed, but into Coverts and Shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? How is <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> enlightned by learned and able Judges, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in opening and deciding Caſes and Controverſies, clearing and ſumming up Evidences, pronouncing righteous Judgment, even to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of the obſtinate and deeply-engaged Enemies of our Peace,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi> in his Trial.</note> that their Proceedings were fair and equal? What Iniquity was to be found in the Seats of Judgment before, is yet felt by all Conditions in the Land, and above all by the beſt of Men: What a Set was there of Judges, Juries, and Evidences for the Deſigns of Kings! What Diſcoveries have been made of the Secrets, Plots and Contrivances, hatch'd in Cabals, and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Counſels of our Confederate Enemies, for the Ruin of Church and State, by the appearing of this great Light! By this Light we ſee the Pathes of our Deſtroyers, and the ſtupendious Providences of God in countermining their pernicious Endeavours. By this Light we know where we were bought and ſold; and whither ſome of us were gone, and others going. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of the nature and benefit of Light; <hi>Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever maketh manifeſt, is Light,</hi> Epheſ. 5.15. It is from this Light we have ſuch full diſcoveries of the ſecret Counſels of Conſpirators; and by this Light we have the things that belong to our Peace laid open to our Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the way of Peace pointed out, if we have but Wiſdom and Hearts to walk therein. What a Light and Joy did their Aſcent into the Throne (God making them way to it) bring to the Oppreſſed in theſe Kingdoms, and to our perſecuted Brethren from abroad? It was the ſpringing of their Light, that gave cauſe to the Reformed Churches to ſing, <hi>The Winter is paſt, or paſſing away, that the Rain is over and gone.</hi> O what a cold Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was it in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Valleys,</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to them who by a Chriſtian Sympathy felt their Cold! How hungry and cold, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and miſerable were our perſecuted Brethren, that were driven from their Houſes, ſtripp'd naked, without as much as the ſhorteſt or thinneſt covering of their Nakedneſs, (cruel Impudence of the moſt inhumane de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate part of Mankind, worſe than Brutes, as bad as Devils could make
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29877:15"/>them, or deſire them to be!<note place="margin">See the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Perſecution in <hi>France, Savoy</hi> and <hi>Orange:</hi> And Mouſ. <hi>Jurieu</hi>'s Letters.</note>) How miſerable a Sight was it to ſee Death ſit upon their Faces, and worſe than Death about them, their worſe than barbarous Heatheniſh Enemies? How miſerable was their Bondage under them? worſe than <hi>Egypt;</hi> for in <hi>Egypt</hi> the People of God had Fleſh-pots and Onions; ſuch as the Earth did yield, ſuch they did eat: But theſe perſecuted Fellow-members of the ſame Body had ſcarce Morſels of Bread knodden with dirty Water, Dirt and Gravel, to keep them from utter ſtarving, when not any of this impenitent, ſtupid, carnal Generation, who live after the Fleſh, and mind the things of the Fleſh, felt the Cold, the Nakedneſs, and pinching Bitterneſs of that Winter. Our Proteſtant Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>France, Savoy, Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> do rejoice in this Light, to feel ſo much of the Winter paſt over, as they have done; and to ſee ſo much of the Rain (the Tribulation that beats upon the Houſe, and tries whether it be built on the Rock or the Sand) blown over and gone. It is becauſe of this Light that the Flowers appear on the Earth, the time of the Singing of Birds is come, and the Voice of the Turtle is heard in our Land.<note place="margin">Cantic. 2.11, 12.</note> O that the blindeſt and perverſeſt among us had Eyes to ſee this great Light, that now ſhines upon our Land! 'Tis true indeed, our Lights come ſhort of Omniſcience; all things are not naked and bare unto them, they cannot ſee in ſecret, and know not what is in Man, as our Saviour did, when he did not commit himſelf to them who came in unto him. They are as far from Infallibility as they are from Popery; the Darkneſs and the Light are not alike to them; they know not the ſecret Practices of Men, who love Golden Days, who are Buyers and Sellers of Places of Truſt, and who are ſo falſe in their Dealings, that their Bribers cannot have their Bargains. All Men of Underſtanding and Buſineſs obſerve and talk of theſe things where they may. There are Caterpillars and Locuſts ſo thick in our Air, that they darken the Glory of our Light, and leave an ill Savour behind them. But though our Lights are not perfect Lights and omniſcient, yet let us adore and praiſe the Lord for giving them ſo much of all Royal Qualifications, and for giving them to us to be a Light, as it is this day. And there are two Bleſſings of ſingular Conſideration to us, as a matter of Praiſe that they are ſo, and a matter of Prayer that they may continue ſo. 1. Each one is a Light to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And, 2. Both are united in one Light. 3. And both are ours.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That our King is a great Light, and ſo was from the morning of his appearance in the World. He is a Lamp in the illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Orange,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Biſhop <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Letter from <hi>Nimiguen.</hi>
                  </note> whoſe here ick Poogenitors embraced, profeſſed, and maintained the Light of the glorious Goſpel ſhining forth in the Reformation; and none of them were aſhamed or afraid to own it. It is glorious to be a Light from his early appearance to be a Prince: Had he been a Wo to the Land by being a Child. or Debauched, or Cowardly, Fear, and Intereſt, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample had ſpoil'd him from ever being a Light to any Nation: He knew
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29877:16"/>his Religion, and kept it, when to change Religions was ſo much in faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: He knew his temporal Rights and Intereſt, and recovered them, and hath ſacrificed them, as he did himſelf, to the Intereſt of the Proteſtant Churches, whoſe declining and almoſt-ruined State would have made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Princes afraid to put forth a hand to preſerve them. And his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for the almoſt-ruined falling Reformed Churches, was ſo much the more admirable, when there was no Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> on the Throne of <hi>England</hi> to ſecond and aſſiſt him and them; and a devouring Prince breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out Deſtruction and Slaughter ſo near him; a Prince that is called Great, truly ſo, from the great Miſeries he hath brought even upon his own Kingdom, to make all others ſo, that by the Judgment of God fall into his Hand: Yet the poverty and weakneſs of Proteſtant Churches, and the Mightineſs of a King, who is like Hell and the Grave, and the Aſſiſtance and Opportunities he had to perfect his Work from <hi>England,</hi> could not make our Light muſſie himſelf in a Cloud, and ſometimes look out to the Waters of a Flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d drowning the World in Miſeries, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ark of the Proteſtant Churches in pieces, and himſelf at eaſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all diſhonourable Conditions to ſave himſelf from Labour and Hazard. O what cauſe have we to adore the al-wiſe Providence and Grace of God, that wrought Truth upon his Heart, inſpired his Head with great Thoughts, and his great Soul with the moſt vigorous Spirit of Fortitude and Zeal, admirably tempered with Calmneſs and Peaceableneſs; and after he had been exerciſed, and given great proofs of his Royal Accompliſhments, to give ſuch a Prince to us, at that time one of the unhappieſt People in the World, and next door to our being the moſt miſerable If his Enemies had but a ſerious deſire of being happy, they would chooſe to be his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and if his Subjects had but wiſdom and grace to acknowledg that Goodneſs, Mercy and Power of God, who ſet him over us, with as clear a manifeſtation of Mercy to us, as of Juſtice in making the Throne vacant for him, they would never hang off, and ſuſpend the Acts of their moſt chearful Obedience, to embolden our Enemies to attempt what we pray they may never perform. He is a King rarely prepared and accompliſhed for Peace or War; by his Sword to force to make it, and by his Wiſdom and Juſtice to keep it: In him there is an immediate Paſſage from the Fountain of Light; and thoſe Rays which are ſcattered in other great Men, are united in him: He is a Light to deliver and ſave from Deſtruction, (a Deliverer is a ſweeter Name than a Conqueror.). To be a Saviour, is to be like God, not in Power only to ſave but in Mercy and Goodneſs; a Name that is to be a Memorial, to admoniſh a People of paſt Miſeries, and reſtored Mercies, and obliges a People to Gratitude and Obedience.—<hi>And according to thy manifold Mercies thou gaveſt them Saviours,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nehem. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>who ſaved them out of the Hand of their Enemies.</hi> Other Nations have had but one Light commonly in an Age; but God hath beſtowed upon us two at once, as knowing our need
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29877:16"/>of more than one, and to ſhew theſe Nations plainly, that he hath not at all dealt with us after our Sins, for then our preſent Day, and Noonday-Light had been as dark as the darkeſt Miſt, terrifying Tempeſt, darker than the darkeſt Night, even as dark as Hell. The Creator of the World made two great Lights, the one to rule by Day, the other by Night; but both our Lights appeared and ſhone upon us out of a Chaos of confuſed Matter in the Nation, which were not like the Epicurean Atoms, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the World, which affecting one another at firſt meeting, made a Marriage, and begat a World of Creatures; no, in our Chaos there was ſo much of Hatred and Diſaffection, ſo much of mutual Fear and Suſpition, that we had fallen one upon another, as Men in their Drink and Madneſs ſight in the dark. We are more and better united, (tho, alas, far from being all of one piece, as a Staff of Beauty in their Majeſties Hands) than we ſhould have been (unleſs common Suffering had made us more one) by the approach of our Light, the Peace and the Union we have by the means of our ſupreme Rulers. But as God hath made nothing in vain, ſo he hath not given us two Lights at once, but becauſe one cannot be abroad and at home at once. God hath wonderfully provided for us; he hath taught us by experience that two are better than one. Let no Man affirm that a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may not be born for Civil Rule and Government: we have been hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py now two years in the Queen's Government; and happier we had been, if all Men had done their Parts in Counſels and Arms, as ſhe did, by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied Diligence, Courage and Patience: That the Queen ſhould be a Light alſo, and ſit to rule the Day of our Mercies, is indeed no leſs than a Wonder: ſhe is a Light, were ſhe not a Queen; but ſhe is a Queen, and therefore the greater Light: She is an illuſtrious Light, for Knowledg in the Truth, not in the Notion and Argument, in oppoſition to Error, but in the Practice, wherein the Power lieth. She is a Light for Wiſdom, piercing into the Myſteries of State, and the difficult parts of her Office. She is made for the Rule of a Palace, for the Retirement of a Cloſet, for exemplary Reverence in the Worſhip and Houſe of God: She is a glorious Beam of Majeſty in her Perſon; ſhe ſhines as ſhe moves; ſhe is made for a Throne, and long may ſhe ſit upon it. She is a diffuſive Light, as ſhe is a joint Cauſe of the true Light of the Goſpel, and the Laws of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs. All People may be as holy, and as righteous as they can deſire; and if they are not, it is their own fault, they have no Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement but Encouragement from above. She is a great Light,<note place="margin">See her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Anſw. to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of the Diſſenting Miniſters.</note> even to a Zeal, in her own Way, and is to be an Example of Moderation towards others; Her Light ſhines before Men, that others ſeeing her good Works may glorify God. Thus each one is a ſingular Light. But yet further what is the greater Mercy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They both make one Light. Through God's infinite Mercy to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and us, that they are ſo much one; they are one Blood, one Fleſh,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29877:17"/>and what is more, of one Heart and one Soul. What a Light are both in one to their whole Dominion, to all their Subjects! It is a vulgar, but a great Obſervation, When had we a King and Queen of one Religion, and both of ours? We have known the lamentable effects and iſſues of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Religions, and of one and the ſame Religion, in our former Kings and Queens. The Light of the one never did convince or convert the other of Darkneſs;<note place="margin">The Articles of Marriage between Pr. <hi>Charles,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Infanta,</hi> and the Queen the Daughter of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </note> nay, the Light was ſo bound ſometimes, as not to endeavour to work upon the Darkneſs, but the Night had power to tempt the Light, and then was one Hour and Power of Darkneſs: and from that time to this moſt bleſſed Conjunction of both our Lights in one, the Darkneſs over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the true Light. O the Calamities and Confuſions, Convulſions and Breaches, which followed after the prevailing Power of Darkneſs! The Darkneſs brought forth Thunder and Lightning, and rained Blood; it brought forth Wars and Fires; it cooled the zeal of many, and made the Nation too hot for others. O what Matter is this for a Faſt, to make Prayers and Supplications, to deprecate thoſe great Evils! And the noiſom Vapours of that Darkneſs make us a ſickly, diſeaſed People to this time. O that the diſeaſed diſtempered People of theſe Nations would come to our Light! O that God would proſper our Light, to bring us to a better Conſtitution and State of a Body united and compacted together! Do not we ſee the excellency of our Light in reſpect of Union? Do not both walk in the ſame Spirit? O what a Mercy is that to us, and to other Nations confederate with us! By this we have a Concord in Counſels, we are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the Plague of Jeſuitical Agitators and Satanical Dividers. Court-Faction have no countenance, nor Whiſperers ſecret Audience; and innumerable other Miſchiefs are prevented: for now the Devil hath leſs to do in Court, and hath fewer Pupils to inſtruct in miſchievous Arts and Practices, between King and Queen, Court and Court. The dividing of the King and Queen in Intereſts, in Affection according to that Intereſt, the dividing of Counſels to promote thoſe different Intereſts, and theſe to be managed by contrary Factions and Parties, and for theſe to love the one and hate the other, ſhould be as dreadful, as if the Stars divided the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens into two Fields, and ſought one againſt another. This is one of the Mercies of this great Revolution, that our Lights are ſo intirely one; and that the Conſtitution of the Government is made ſo ſtrong, that our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viders cannot divide, but they muſt break and diſſolve: many would have it otherwiſe; but God wrought ſuch a Temper in the Spirit of the Queen, as to ſubmit the Precedence given her by Nature, for the publick Benefit. And that the Memories of both be bleſſed for ever; and whatever Breaches remain unhealed among a ſinful People, many of whom know not the things of their own Peace, O Lord, ſhine into the Hearts of theſe two great Lights, that they may reign as one.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And yet the Matter grows higher ſtill; Theſe two illuſtrious Lamps
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29877:17"/>made one Light, are both the Light of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The Light of <hi>David</hi>'s Life, as I noted before, was the Light of <hi>Iſrael. David</hi> was to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to himſelf; and <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to <hi>David,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> was to himſelf. The Light of <hi>David</hi> was their Light; <hi>That thou quench not the Light of Iſrael.</hi> So is our <hi>David</hi> ours. And without flattery, which I abhor, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially on a ſolemn Day of Confeſſion and Humiliation, but to convince you of your Mercy and Duty, I ſpeak to you theſe Words of Truth and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſs. What clearer Evidence can any People have, whoſe Reaſons are not perverted againſt Senſe, to be in the untoward Party of Murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and Complainers, than our <hi>David</hi> hath given us of his appearance, coming forth, and goings on, but for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and for the ſcattered Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſcattered by Perſecutors into many Nations? What hath he done, in all he hath done, for himſelf? What hath he not done, that could be done for us?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> O but Murmurers and Papiſts, and their old dear Friends, ſay, <hi>He ſought the Throne, and is come unto it by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is ſuch an Imagination as could never enter into the Heart of Man that believes a Providence, and that all the Actions of Princes, as well as other Men, are ſubject to it; and that Kings and Princes cannot do, and have what they will. How many apparent Hazards by Sea and Land did he neceſſarily foreſee, and every ſtep might preſent him with Death, which was enough to quench the Spark of Ambition, and deter him from an Uſurpation? It would have been the moſt irrational Project that could ever come into a wiſe Man's Head, and viſibly improbable, if not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as I would undertake to demonſtrate, if time would give leave. God ſent him in as a Deliverer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and ſo he was acknowledged, even by them who will not ſwear Fidelity to him now, their only King by Law and Right. But if I might ask thoſe Men theſe few Queſtions, what could they ſay? 1. What hath he asked for himſelf? what hath he employed for, or ſpent upon himſelf, ſince his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Arrival? Hath he got half what one half Year's Revenue by Hearths would have brought him in? Was there ever a Free-holder in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, before he reſtored them? Nay, to ſilence ſome of theſe Male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Do not they, ſome of them, to diſcourage the Nation, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Enemies, give out, that he will not be able to manage the War for want of Money, and for the vaſt Debt that is upon the Nation? So then, this was a hopeful Project to invade the Throne, to want what he never wanted before, <hi>viz.</hi> Money. If the Throne was ambitiouſly ſought, why did he not, and why doth he not ſit at Eaſe upon it? Or why doth he not make Peace with <hi>France,</hi> and do as his Predeceſſors did? Or why might not he work upon the Counſels of <hi>France</hi> to ſend away the late King, as the Uſurpers formerly did, when both the late Kings were Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Exile? Why may not Engliſh Money work as much in <hi>France</hi> now,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29877:18"/>as French Money doth work in <hi>England?</hi> Or why doth he not ſtay at home to reak and revenge himſelf on ſome of the Murmurers at home? Why doth he not feed the Debauched with Money and Favours, and give them an Example of Vanities, Sports, Pleaſures, and make more Flood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates of Wickedneſs and Vice, than were opened before? If he would but enrich ſome, as he might at cheaper rates, than one Expedition, and ſacrifice himſelf wholly to their Service, who call themſelves The Church, and run into their Methods, he might enjoy the ſweet of his Uſurpation, (as they call it) and not bring in Popery neither. There are far eaſier Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods to enjoy a ſinful Reſt, to eat the Marrow and Fatneſs of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, than by the reſtleſs Pains of a Warrior.</p>
               <p>To ſay no more upon this Head, I conclude with mine own Belief, when I conſider the Foot-ſteps of Divine Providence, his righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the former Powers, and his placing their Majeſties in ſupream Authority, and their great Endeavours and Fitneſs for the Service of God in this Age, and what hath been done, I admire the Mercy of our Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, and look upon our inſtrumental National Saviours, to be the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God to us for good; and I do believe that God hath intruſted the King with the Government of theſe Nations, that he might have the greater Power for further Service, and greater than what is yet done: I fear the Impenitence, and retaining the Abominations of many Years paſt, more than all the Armies of our Enemies.</p>
               <p>O let not our Sins provoke God to darken our Light, and to leave us under thoſe Judgments we have long deſerved! O that we had Hearts affected with our Mercies, Deliverances, and Duties! O that ſuch Lights had no malignant Stars near their Perſons, and in all their Truſts! I have ſaid, what hath the King ſought for himſelf? but O what great things has he done for us in a little time? O how much more might he have done, had there not been many Obſtructions among our ſelves? O let us argue our ſelves into a due Senſibleneſs, that we may be thankful, and contribute all our Endeavours in our ſeveral places for the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. It is a particular, and conſidering our State and Circumſtances then and now, a wonderful Mercy of God, to bring into <hi>England</hi> ſuch a Light and Lamp, whoſe Beams put ſuch a Vigor and Spirit of Life into the almoſt-quenched Hopes of Deliverance in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> as well as <hi>England</hi> (which was in the beſt Condition of the three, and the beſt of the three) brought nigh to the ſides of the Pit of Deſtruction; who could hope for any Good but what was brought to us over the Heads and tops of Mountains of Oppoſition? beſides them, who can make fair Weather in any Alterations, and ſerve the worſt as well as beſt of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, for Honour, Power and Profit? How many were among us, that did not know whether it were beſt to be ſaved or loſt? Sleep in a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29877:18"/>whole Skin in the Night of Popery, or live like free Men and Chriſtians under the Light of Liberty and Religion, until they ſaw the Powers of Darkneſs diſſolved, and the Light coming on proſperouſly by the Favour of an irreſiſtible Providence? The Mercy is, it is Light, not Fire, Light, not Lightning; it is Light with an admirable temper of Heat, not a ſcorching Sun. It is a moderate, kind, beneficent, growing Light; it doth leiſurely exalt and ſpend the noiſom Vapours, Fuſtineſs, Damps and ill Scents of a Houſe before infected: But as great a Bleſſing as it is, it is but a Lamp, and will go out, if it ſhould not be put out and quenched: O what a dark confounded Houſe would it be if the Lamp ſhould be quenched! If it be a Lamp, and but a Lamp, what ſhould the Family do?</p>
               <p n="1">1. All the Servants of God ſhould bleſs and praiſe the Lord who afforded us a Light: O bleſs the mighty and merciful Hand of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which brought us a Light in the Night of Confuſions and Fears! The Enemies of God dwelt in the Houſe before, their Hearts were turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away from Truth, Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Love to their Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, even to Children, as well as all Ranks and Degrees of Officers and Servants: They had the Art of making Promiſes which they never kept; and gave an Indulgence to ſuch as they always hated, and could not love without a miraculous Alteration of Nature: Lay them firſt aſleep in their Boſom, and then ſtrangle them when they were aſleep, if they had had but ſo much time for it: and inſtead of preſerving good Government, they brought in Thieves and Cut-throats: Nothing could have made theſe run away and hide in all haſte, but the ſpringing in of Light, and ſetting up a Lamp attended with ſtrong Guards of reſolute Men, againſt whom they thought it would be but Folly to fight. This was the mighty Work of God, and a merciful Deliverance!</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us love the Light, and ſhew that we love it, by contributing all we can to make it ſhine the brighter, and glorify God the more, by ſaving others, as we our ſelves were ſaved.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let us interpoſe between him and them that hate him, that we may preſerve him: There are ſecret and open Haters of him, Conſpirators that conſpire to blow him out, Neutrals that will neither blow him out nor keep him in; and here is another ſort of them who wiſhed him in, and when he was in, wiſhed him out; that promiſe Peace and Duty, but will not ſwear to be true and loyal, or if they ſwear, it is with a Proviſo that this new Oath conſiſts with their former to another King: We muſt labour to tie theſe up ſome other way, and preſerve our Light from them. And there are open Enemies by Sea and Land, Armies of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines, and armed <hi>Iſhbi-benobs,</hi> that would put out our Light. The more theſe do hate him, let us love him the more, and let their Hatred of him and us be one reaſon to encreaſe our Love to him: His open and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Enemies are all our Enemies; let us count them ſo, and for the reſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29877:19"/>we ought to beware of them; and if their Conſciences are ſo tied up by their miſtaken Oaths, add two Bands more upon them, one upon their Tongues, and another upon their Hands.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let us make the uttermoſt Benefit we can of the Light, while it ſhines upon us. What would many wiſe and good Men have given for ſuch a King and Queen? and for the Opportunity but of ſome one Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament as we have had? We thankfully acknowledg the Settlement of their Royal Majeſties in the Throne, and the Succeſſion of the Crown, and the Liberties of the People: We gratefully acknowledg the Wiſdom and Clemency of God in their Majeſties choice of great Men of Temper for the Candle-ſticks of their Sees: We hope theſe will not think their Eyes ſo full of ſight as to uſe others as if they had none, but muſt reſign their Conſciences to their Conduct, and drive them by force if they will not follow. We hope and pray, that as one Light hath brought forth more, ſo all theſe Lights will find out and ſhew us the true Path of Church-Peace and Concord. Let us hope that that Obſervation may not be a Proverb any more in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> That Biſhops always hindred the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Reformation. As God made way for their Majeſties Coming to the Throne of the Kingdom by a Vacancy, ſo he hath made way for their coming to their Thrones in their Churches. How many Vacancies hath God made by Death? and how many Vacancies have others made by themſelves? And will they do nothing for God, more than they who have always done too little one way, and too much another? Enough hath been ſaid and written to file off the Aſperity and Roughneſs of the temper of their Predeceſſors: and every Succeſſion exceeded the former in Impoſitions, for which they pleaded Obedience more from the Supremacy of our Kings, and Obedience to the Laws, than the Nature of the things themſelves, or their Expediency: but we have ſeen gracious Offers from our ſupream Governours at a temper, therefore we fear no Obſtruction from them, and they have ſeen who they were that oppoſed it, and have retarded it, and know how they ſtand affected. And ſurely now once again we may hope that they will not love their Enemies and hate their Friends: God hath made way for it, and the beſt in the Nation expect it. <hi>Walk in the Light while you have the Light,</hi> ſaid Chriſt; take the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity while you have it. In our Prayers for our Monthly-Faſts, we do acknowledg there are Dregs in the Reformed Churches, which we pray God to purge away: Are not we one of thoſe Reformed Churches? and are theſe Dregs only in Foreign Churches, and none in ours? O ſee them, and purge them out while we have Light to help us!</p>
               <p n="5">5. Are our Lights but Lamps that may be quenched, or if not quenched by Violence, will go out of Courſe? then this is one reaſon of the Mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the beſt State of a Kingdom; and therefore good Kings do mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oblige their Subjects and Poſterity alſo. When they ſpend their Days
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29877:19"/>and Abilities in a holy, religious, righteous, active and diligent courſe of Government; when they lay out themſelves continually from a Principle of ſincere Love to God and his Glory, and their Peoples Happineſs; for they know not how ſoon their Light may be quenched, and then they are for ever laid aſide, and can do no good to themſelves nor their Subjects.</p>
               <p n="6">6. May our Lights be quenched? O then, when Kings prepare for War and Battel, how piouſly ſhould they prepare for Death, and bleſs God for Life when they come off with it. They who carry their Lives in their Hands, who fear not the Face of an Enemy, not of an <hi>Iſhbi-benob,</hi> ſhould therefore fear God, who can kill the Body and the Soul, and caſt both into Hell: O fear him! It will be an everlaſting Shame and Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to fall under the Power of Death, as an Enemy to God. When they carry the Weapons of War, how careful ſhould they be to put on the whole Armour of God! What wiſe King will ingage in a War, and make no Preparation for it, that deſigns not to conquer? What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable Raſhneſs and Madneſs is it for a King that is wiſe and valiant in the Eyes of Man, to be unprovided for the laſt Enemy? True, he ſhall be deſtroyed; but by whom? Chriſt, and he who doth ſavingly believe in him: And Death deſtroys all that are not the living Members of Chriſt, that are not ſaved by Grace; and with what Shame and Contempt ſhall they riſe out of their Graves (which vain Men call a Bed of Honour, though they come to it by diſhonouring God) that died in their Sin, and not in Chriſt or in the Faith, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Patriarchs did? <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. May the Lamps of <hi>Iſrael</hi> be quenched? O then, as truly as we love and honour them, let us not idolize them, nor think of them above what we ought to think! <hi>Curſed is the Man that truſteth in Man, and maketh Fleſh his Arm, and whoſe Heart departeth from the Lord,</hi> i. e. by truſting in Man, and making the Fleſh his Arm, that is, his Confidence and Strength, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5. This is the way to bring a Curſe upon our ſelves, and Death upon the Arm we truſt upon: It was a Preſage of an approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Death to that great Deliverer, that died in his Glory, <hi>Guſtavus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> he thought God would e're long take him away, becauſe the People did over-value and deify him.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you, let us pray and ſtudy for a true Chriſtian Temper of Spirit towards the Lord of Hoſts our King, and the Cauſe of God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let us aſſuredly look upon our King as a great Inſtrument in the Hand of the Lord of Hoſts. 2. The number of his Years are with God. 3. His Work is meaſured out to him by God. 4. Our Light ſprang out of great Obſcurity and from very ſmall Beginnings;<note place="margin">See Biſhop <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Lett. from <hi>Nimiguen.</hi>
                  </note> it was a great ſign of following Succeſſes, and that he was ſingled out for great Actions, when he was not afraid to encounter the moſt potent King of his Age, growing greater daily by Succeſſes, and in his full Strength, when the Condition of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29877:20"/>the States was deſperate and irrecoverable, if the then young Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had but deſpaired alſo: but even then he gave a check to that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growing Oppreſſor, and is, by the great Power of God being with him, grown to be formidable to him; and may the Sound of his Name, by the Terror of the Almighty, make his Sleep to depart from him, and his Heart tremble, when he thinks and conſulteth what to do. 5. What would we have God to do for us, that he hath not done, or is not ready to do? Some conſidering, true hearted, wiſe Obſervers, have faithfully declared what they thought to be the cauſe of many Miſcarriages in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> by Sea and Land; and in particular, ſince our Monthly-Faſts were laid down and intermitted, God hath not gone on to do us good, though he hath not utterly departed from us. But though our Sins have with-held good things from us, we are in a better State both at home and abroad, than we were when God ſent us a Deliverer. There is a Generation among us, who have caſt off the Fear of God, a profane, carnal, ſenſual, debauched Multitude, that have always oppoſed the great and only Redeemer Chriſt, and his Intereſt in the Nation, that care no more for the real Proſperity of the Kingdom, than for the turning up of a Dye, high or low, when they throw for nothing, ſo that they may have but enough to maintain their ungodly, fleſhly, and worldly Luſts. Theſe are not for the Pope, but yet they are for Antichriſt and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, for the Kingdom of Darkneſs and Irreligion: Theſe are they whoſe God is their Belly, whoſe Glory is in their Shame, Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt: And to theſe we muſt add another Party (though in other things far different from them, and better Men) who plead an Obligation of Conſcience for Diſloyalty, and theſe do animate and propagate the other (though perhaps not directly) who are diſaffected to Godlineſs and the Government. Nay, the worſt of Men do not only harden them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Diſloyalty, and proceed on to trouble <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or hinder our Settlement, by having the Conſciences of ſome upon their ſide, but they have ſet up a new Title againſt our Government, and that is the Church of <hi>England:</hi> The Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt <hi>England;</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> Is Chriſt divided? Is the Church divided? The Church of <hi>England</hi> we know, but who are ye?—And yet let me ſhew you one other cauſe of the Slowneſs of our Motions towards Settlement and Peace, and raiſing up of the Tabernacle of God, and the ſhining forth of the Beauty of Holineſs. There are loyal Perſons to the Government, who are not refined from the Impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the former Reigns. Thouſands in the Land that run into Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs and Licentiouſneſs out of Cowardice, and to avoid ſome Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names given out to diſgrace real Godlineſs; and being accuſtomed to Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs, out of Fear. And in compliance with moſt ungodly Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, have brought ſuch a Cuſtom upon themſelves, that either they are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29877:20"/>Temporizers with the worſt of Men, or ſin out of choice and love. Some of theſe would, if they could, overthrow the Chariot, others lay Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in its way, and theſe laſt are like Scotches in our Wheels: But our Hope is in God; he ruleth in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and hath given out ſuch Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Goodneſs, that be it known to us, he doth not do what he doth for our ſakes, but what is more effectual, for his own Name ſake: <hi>O then, not unto us, not unto us, but to thy Name give Glory, for thy Mercy and thy Truth's ſake,</hi> Pſal. 115.1. When God ſets his Wheel a going, it ſhall go againſt all Oppoſitions; ſometimes it goes viſibly at a great rate, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more inſenſibly; and when we ſee not the Motions of it, it goes whither the Spirit was to go, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.12. Man may loſe Time and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, but the Spirit of God never loſt, and never will loſe time. 6. The Work of this Generation is God's in an eminent manner, and he will carry it on till all be finiſhed; but he tieth not himſelf to Means and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, therefore ſo ſhould not we. The Work of God hath been and is a Work for Generations; and no one Man is ordained to do all, but many Inſtruments have their ſeveral parts. None is immortal, none invulnera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or impenetrable. Let us therefore believe with confidence that this War is God's, and it is the Hand of God, and our King is one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Inſtruments that God hath uſed; he came up like Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when the Kingdom was weak, like a <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus.</hi> Let us ſee God in him, follow God, and wait upon him, and be careful of him, and by ſtrong Faith, humble Confidence, fervent Prayers, truſt him under the Shadow of the Almighty.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But how can we rejoice and take comfort in Him as the Light of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ſeeing he adventures his Royal Perſon in very dangerous Voyages and Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels? As it would be the greateſt Grief of our Souls to be deprived of him, ſo our Hearts are in daily fear of Evil befalling to him: What would become of us in our divided and diſcontented State, if our Light ſhould be quenched?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. You ſhould conſider that this bright illuſtrious Lamp is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to us alone; I cannot but adore the ſafe and haſty diſpatch which God Alwiſe and Almighty made of the mighty Affair of theſe Kingdoms? How ſoon did the King of Heaven and Earth pull down one, and ſet up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? How ſoon did God make an end of one King's Reign, and begin another's? The King that then was in Arms, a powerful well-prepared and trained Army, almoſt, if not above double the number to thoſe our King brought in, and yet not as much as the ſtop of one Day's march or diverſion given, by fighting one Battel! He had time enough for leiſurely and orderly Marches, without any cauſe of Precipitation, or loſing time by committing Errors. What a good Providence was this! Things ſhall be eaſy when God doth ſave; it ſhall be as eaſy as to bid an Army in array to ſtand ſtill, and ſee the Salvation of the Lord; and as ſoon as to ſay,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.17. Neh. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>To morrow ye ſhall go out againſt them, for the Lord will be with you.</hi> So when
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29877:21"/>the Lord doth raiſe a Saviour to his People, he will be with him; and when he is with him, he makes way for him. Had our King conquered by win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning many Battels, and after he had beaten a great Army, been conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſpend much time in long Debates; how miſerable had this Kingdom been by Fears and Factions! And to what Neceſſities had foreign Nations been preſſed? <hi>Ireland</hi> certainly loſt, <hi>Scotland</hi> confounded, if not ruined. But he who ruleth over all, was pleaſed to ſave us, and ſettle us with great expedition, that his Servant <hi>David</hi> might go forth againſt the Philiſtines. What Treacheries with Obſtructions were uſed to hinder him from ſaving <hi>Ireland</hi> in time, may be with trouble remembred; that ſome People who appeared forward to embrace Deliverance, withdrew their Help, as if they had repented of doing any thing to make themſelves happy, and ſave others from utter Ruin. How many wiſhed the King might not go to <hi>Ireland</hi> in Perſon, that the Loſs of <hi>Ireland</hi> might be imputed to him? And others were for his going, that he might never return again, or in his Abſence our Enemies might make work in <hi>England.</hi> Some honeſt Hearts wiſhed he would not go, being afraid of Commotions in his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and Danger to his Perſon: Others prayed for his going, and when gone, for his Proſperity and ſafe Return; and we have rejoiced for both, out with ſome trembling, for God rebuked us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſide the Intereſts of many Nations united in him, he is led into the beſt way and method of ſecuring and ſaving us at home, by going to meet the great Enemy abroad; and if God be with him there, we ſhall reap the Benefit of it here.<note place="margin">Balthazaris Ayala, De jure Off. bell. <hi>l. 4. c. 2.</hi>
                  </note> It hath been variouſly adjudged by great Commanders, whether it is better to keep at home, and receive Enemies from abroad, and repel them; or carry the War abroad into the Enemies Countries: But certainly the Reaſons and Circumſtances of this War, well known to our wiſe King, perſwade it is beſt where it is. God hath provided for us a wiſe, watchful, couragious Queen, in full Authority to govern and watch over us at home, who is worthy to be truſted under God. There are more Princes engaged in this War beſide the King, and other Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerned: and if God do but break that Devourer at home, and deal with him, as God rewarded <hi>Adonibezek,</hi> it will keep him from ravaging abroad, as he hath done: Hunt him down, he will be glad to hide in his own Den. Nothing is more to be fear'd than a Compoſition with him; for being faithleſs, he will no longer keep Conditions of Peace, than he can gather Strength to break them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You ſay, you would not have him venture his Perſon. I ſay, let us expreſs all the loyal and truly-Chriſtian Care we can, and all the true Zeal we can for his Preſervation; but let us conſider, that it hath been the manner and uſe of the greateſt Kings, and the beſt of Commanders, to go to the Wars, and command in Battels: Not to ſpeak of the famous Conquerors of the World, was there ſuch a Man in the World as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:29877:21"/>was?<note place="margin">Gen. 14.13, 14, 15, 16.</note> And this holy <hi>Abraham</hi> goes in the Head of his armed Men in Perſon, and leaves not the charge of them to his Confederates: How like a Souldier did he command and marſhal his Men; and he was not a Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, but an Actor in the Fight. What a Man was <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who had the Name and Spirit of a Saviour: he went, and did not take care to ſend to the Battels of the Mighty. The ſame might be enlarged in <hi>David,</hi> even to a declining Age; and of other Kings.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A King may be as ſafe in a Camp as in his Court; read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.5. <hi>I laid me down and ſlept; I awaked, for the Lord ſuſtained me.</hi> Ver. 6. <hi>I will not be afraid of ten thouſands of People, that have ſet themſelves againſt me round about. Ariſe, O Lord, ſave me, O my God,</hi> &amp;c. Pſal. 27.3, 4, 5. But then remember, theſe Men were ſtrong in Faith, and much in Prayer.</p>
               <p>Not to exceed in length; Let us who are ſenſible of the great Favour of God towards us in our King and Queen, be upon our Duties, which are two. 1. Truſt. 2. Prayer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Truſt God with all our Heart. Look upon our Lamps as ſubject to Mortality, to fainting, to be quenched, but let us look to the God of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> above the ſading Light of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Iſa. 45.22. <hi>Look unto me, and be ye ſaved all the Ends of the Earth: for I am God, and none elſe.</hi> Kings cannot ſave themſelves, but it is God <hi>who giveth Salvation to Kings,</hi> Pſal. 144.10. <hi>Salvation belongeth to the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 3.8.<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.6. Pſal. 33.16 2 Chron. 14, 11.</note> And a King that truſteth in the Lord, will not truſt to his Bow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the greateſt Numbers of Men, nor Preparations for War. He was a King and a Prophet that dehorteth us from truſting in Princes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Truſt the Lord of Hoſts with our King and Queen. As we are to caſt all our private Burdens upon the Lord, and to commit our private Ways, Affairs, and Concernments, to the Lord; ſo let us caſt the great Concernment of the Kingdom, and all the People of God in the Kingdom. The King truſteth in the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.7. O let us truſt alſo in the Lord, and truſt our Light to his gracious, watchful, and mighty Providence.</p>
               <p>O that we could truſt the mighty God of <hi>Jacob</hi> with his Church and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when as low and weak as <hi>Jacob;</hi> when he is called <hi>Jacob, Jacob</hi> is low and weak: Now is the time for right truſting in God. And the more Truſt and Confidence we place in the King and Queen, and the more we exceed in love to them, the more cauſe have we to have a right Truſt in God.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) Truſt the King as far as a King is to be truſted, with our Armies, with our Purſes, with our national Intereſts abroad and at home; and the more our diſaffected Back-friends have contemned him, let us honour and truſt him the more. But when we have truſted much to his Wiſdom, Integrity, Valour, Conduct and Experience, let us not make an Idol of him; let us not forget God, nor forget that he it is that teacheth his Hands to war, and his Fingers to fight.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Truſt God in this Cauſe and War, as if we had no King to truſt to, for we muſt truſt God alone: <hi>Only the Lord be with thee, as he was with</hi> Moſes, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 1.17. <hi>He only is my Rock and my Salvation; he is my Defence, I ſhall not be greatly moved. My Soul wait thou only upon God: for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29877:22"/>my Expectation is from him. He only is my Rock and my Salvation: I ſhall not be moved. In God is my Salvation and my Glory: the Rock of my Strength, and my Refuge is in God. Truſt in him at all times, ye People—Surely Men of low degree are Vanity; and Men of high degree are a Lye,</hi> Pſal. 62.2, 5, <hi>&amp;c. It is better to truſt in the Lord, than to put confidence in Princes,</hi> Pſal. 118.9. <hi>All Nations compaſſed me about, but in the Name of the Lord I will deſtroy them,</hi> verſ. 10.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Truſt not in Means with the leaſt neglect of God, yet uſe God's Means in truſting God. Truſt God in the uſe of Means, above Means; truſt not God without Means, when Means may be had of God's appointment. <hi>Set your ſelves in array, but then ſtand ſtill and ſee the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord,</hi> 2 Chron. 20.17. <hi>David</hi> would not truſt in his Bow, but he would make uſe of his Bow. Though the Means be but as Rams-horns, and the tumbling of Barley-loaves, yet do as God would have us. Preſumption is no Truſt.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) Truſt God with giving, ſupplying, renewing, diſpoſing and proſpering Means, but do not limit God to any one Way, or Time, or Perſon. <hi>Mordecai</hi> was a Wonder; he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that God would deliver the Jews, he made uſe of <hi>Heſter</hi> as a proper, as a very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Inſtrument to work upon the King; but his Truſt was not limited to her; but if ſhe fail'd, Deliverance ſhall come from another place, <hi>Heſter</hi> 4.14. No King in <hi>England,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſhonour to any, was ſo like to carry on the Work of God, and to do the Service of his Church, as our preſent King is; he hath done much already. Was ever King ſo truſted by ſo many Princes? Who was ſo engaged, being ſo provoked by the Enemy, ſo prepared with depth of Thoughts and Privacy, with Induſtry beyond Strength; or encouraged by Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances as He? Yet ſtill let us not limit the moſt High God; and the more we truſt God, the more we love our King. O long may this Lamp burn and ſhine; but he can no longer give Light to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> than the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> goes before him, and bears him up in his Hand.</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) Truſt God in all Dangers, to preſerve him and ſuccour him in caſe of fainting. God has ſuccoured him by one of his Nobles, in a former Battel againſt <hi>France.</hi> Let us pray and truſt, that Help ſhall not be far from him when Dangers are nigh.</p>
               <p>O let all that fear the Lord, truſt in the Lord: Now let our Eyes be towards the Lord, and truſt him over all; truſt him, I ſay, again, with our Light and Lamp. And O that we could truſt God, not with a humane Truſt, as far as we ſee great Armies, and early Succeſſes, but truſt God with the Truſt of humble, penitent, believing, ſincere, praying Hearts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>2d</hi> Duty is Prayer; and this is one part of the whole Armour of God, without which who can expect to be ſaved? Great and many were <hi>David</hi>'s Extremities, and therefore we find ſo many of his Prayers and Thankſgivings for their Succeſs. They who pray moſt and beſt, are God's beſt Servants, and the King's trueſt Subjects. O let us pray by Faith, with Hope, with Contrition, Humiliation, Sincerity, Fervency, Continuance and Perſeverance, by the Spirit, in the Name and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, to the Lord of Hoſts, to God mighty in Battel. When <hi>David</hi> ſpake of the peaceable and proſperous Reign of <hi>Solomon,</hi> he ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 72.15</note> and <hi>for him ſhall Prayer be made continually.</hi> O all you that can pray, pray heartily, pray daily, pray abundantly. Prayer has been moſt prophanely derided in this Age: But if we would have God do what we will, let us believe and pray according to the Will of God: Let not a day paſs over you, without effectual Prayers for God's Glory in the proſperity of the Goſpel, and redeeming <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of all his Troubles. And that God would guide, aſſiſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and proſper our King and Queen, and ſtrengthen them by his Spirit in the inner Man, take theſe following Conſiderations to ſatisfy and encourage your Hearts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The King muſt go to theſe Wars: It is not Vanity to ſee the young Men play before him, as <hi>Abner</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joab,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.14. Heſt. 4.14.</note> no, but neceſſity. A neceſſity in reſpect of Duty and Obedience to God, who hath prepared and called him to it. He is obliged to aſſiſt in a Common Cauſe againſt a Common Deſtroyer of Countries and Cities. <hi>And who knoweth but he is come to the Kingdom for ſuch a Time,</hi> for ſuch a Service <hi>as this?</hi> He doth not only add Strength by his Armies, but puts Life into the Armies of other Princes as well as his own. There is the ſame Neceſſity for our King to go forth to Battel, as it was for <hi>David</hi>'s going when he went; it may be ſo,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29877:22"/>that there may not be hereafter a like Neceſſity, as there was not when the Men of <hi>David</hi> obliged him not to go; for then he was much diſabled, and there were many others fit for the Service that were forward to go, Men fit to be truſted,<note place="margin">Wendeline Doctrin. Politicae. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>42.</hi> &amp; Ayala. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Sect. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> Men that were true to the Happineſs of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And as <hi>Ceſar</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>Not go; but, Come along.</hi> So many other great Captains have not only been preſent, but performed the parts of Souldiers as well as Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals. But the greateſt Valour muſt do this with great Caution, and remember he is a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and not a Commander, poſted to maintain his aſſigned Ground, leſt he become a Mark for an <hi>Iſhbi-benob;</hi> or give cauſe to an Enemy to ſay as he did, who killed the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned King of <hi>Sweden, That is the true Bird;</hi> and ſo ſhot him dead. Let us not forget to ask of God, always to govern the King's great Mind, and guide him with his Eye.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is ſufficient Encouragement for us all, not to be faint-hearted and diſmayed, but to pray with an awful humble Confidence and Expectation, that God will favour this Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Cauſe.</p>
               <p>For, 1. this War is a lawful War, and that gives us encouragement to ſeek God for the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of it, and our good King's Proſperity and Preſervation. The Lawfulneſs of this War will appear in all the Cauſes of a lawful War, if you,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider our Selves. 2. Our Enemies. 3. Our Allies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If you conſider our Selves. It is lawful, becauſe undertaken by Supream Authority; by the King, and Conſent of the Parliament. The King hath juſt cauſe to maintain his own juſt Title to the Crown and Government of theſe Kingdoms: And it is the Peoples Duty to ſerve him in the Wars according to their utmoſt Ability; as <hi>Judah</hi> did adhere to <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.4.</note> whom they received, and anointed him to be their King. You know that I have not made State-Matters the Subject of my Preaching; but now it is neceſſary to ſay ſomething to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you in what I believe is true, and then engage and perſwade you to your Duties. The King's Title and Right to the Crown is ſcrupled by ſome, who own him as King <hi>de facto</hi> in Poſſeſſion; theſe do ſeem rather to temporize, than to obey upon a full Principle of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſpeak not fully to the Point, and the Caſe of the King and Queen: And others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſwear Allegiance to them, though ſettled upon the Throne by a free Convention of Peers and People; and their Title ratified by a Parliament, and acknowledged by all Princes and States abroad, except One who would have the Kingdom for himſelf if he could. Which of all the Heads of the ſeveral Families and Lines of our Engliſh Kings could ſhew a better Title, or near ſo good, than our King and Queen, antecedent to their Coronation? But ſince it ſhould be held undoubted, and therefore this War is lawful, if it were for nothing but to maintain his juſt Title againſt his Enemies. The Reaſons which <hi>Abner,</hi> and the Men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> gave for their ſubmiſſion, were good to prove <hi>David</hi>'s Title; and every one of them might be applied to prove our Soveraign's Title, ſee 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.12, 17, 18. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.2, 3. And though God hath not ſpoken by audible Words to them, <hi>You ſhall feed my People Iſrael, and thou ſhalt be Captain over Iſrael;</hi> he hath ſpoken aloud by convincing Providences.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is lawful if you reſpect our Enemies. The French have declared War againſt us, attempted an Invaſion. Do not we know him too well to let him in? If we reſiſt him, who ſhall be our King? He that hath ſaved us, and doth ſtill endeavour it? or he, who when he had declined, and refuſed to ſatisfy the juſt Petitions of his Subjects, and contrary to Law, and his Duty, went about to change our Government; and not daring to meet a Free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ventured his Cauſe to the determination of God, by the Sword, and loſt it, in that Court of Judgment, and deſerted the Government and Kingdom, and withdrew to an open Enemy's Country, and hath made uſe of that Enemy's Power againſt us; and fled another Kingdom ſince, to that ſame Enemy's Country again? The <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> yea, <hi>Abner</hi> himſelf,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.18. Chap. 5.2.</note> thought <hi>David</hi> was the rightful King, who had gone in and out before the People, and had ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them from all their Enemies. It is a lawful War for us to defend our ſelves againſt an open Enemy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The War of <hi>France</hi> againſt us, is an unlawful War; ſuppoſe it were, as we clearly
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29877:23"/>ſee it is not, with a pure reſpect to the late King; but if it were, it would be our Duty to reſiſt him. 1. He was no lawful King of <hi>England,</hi> according to the Law of <hi>England,</hi> The lawful King of <hi>England,</hi> is Supream in his Dominions, in oppoſition to all Foreign Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions or Power; out he ſubjected himſelf to a Foreign Juriſdiction, and therefore loſt it, and ceaſed to be the King of <hi>England.</hi> 2. There is no Allegiance due to any other, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, but to a Proteſtant King, whom we ſwear to defend in oppoſition to the Uſurpation of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> But the King was a profeſſed Papiſt, and own'd that Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, againſt which we ſwore; Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. He is no King according to our Laws, and therefore an Uſurper and Tyrant, that doth not ſwear to maintain our Laws. He that ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to bring in Popery, forbidden by Law, and to root out the Religion eſtabliſhed by Law, doth not rule by Law; Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That he did en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eavour to do ſo, let us couſult, his Letter written and ſent to the Pope from <hi>Dublin,</hi> now printed at the end of the Lord <hi>Preſton</hi>'s Trial;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nov.</hi> 26. 1689.</note> 
                  <q>Moſt Holy Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The only Source of all theſe Rebellions againſt us is, that we embraced the Catholick Faith; and do nor diſown, but to ſpread the ſame, not only in our three Kingdoms, but over all the diſperſed Colonies of our Subjects in <hi>America,</hi> was our determination.</q> What greater Evidence of his Deſigns and Endeavours to bring in Popery, contrary to our Laws, than this? He was King only in Poſſeſſion: He had been their Expectant, and did actually ſucceed, and had quiet Poſſeſſion by God's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and the Kingdom's Peaceableneſs, till he went about to diſſolve the very Foundations of the Government. And our preſent lawful King, then a Free Prince, and no Subject of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See <hi>Grot. de jure Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li,</hi> l. 2. c. 24. <hi>And the R. R. Bp. of St.</hi> Aſaph<hi>'s Diſcourſe.</hi>
                  </note> came to deliver us, and preſerve our Laws and Liberties, which was a lawful Act. His Invaſion was a lawful Act, and had it produced a War, it had been a lawful War, againſt a King that had fallen from his legal Kingly Supremacy, by his own Fault and Act.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This War is a lawful War, in reſpect of our Confederates, though ſome of them are of a differing Religion from us. Many of them, as well as our King, have received great Injuries from him, and been oppreſſed by him; and all have cauſe more than to ſuſpect him of deſtructive Deſigns by his growing Power, to make a Prey of Neighbouring Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This might eaſily be proved lawful by the Example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 14. of <hi>David</hi> reſcuing <hi>Keilah,</hi> 1 Sam. 23. and made a proſperous War upon <hi>Hadarezar,</hi> 1 Chron. 18.3.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The miſerably oppreſſed Subjects of <hi>France</hi> cry for Aſſiſtance to ſave them periſhing, and reſtore their juſt legal Liberties, and Proteſtant Princes may be moved to engage on the behalf of the Perſecuted Proteſtants, whoſe Liberties and Religion were eſtabliſhed by Edicts and Compacts.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Our gracious Soveraign is engaged in this War by the moſt honourable Engagement that could induce and oblige a King to undertake a War, the Conduct of the Confederates Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies entruſted with him.</p>
               <p>Now what remaineth, but that we all engage our Hearts to God, and heartily concern our ſelves for the Preſervation of his Majeſty's Perſon, under the ſafe Conduct of God and his Angels? An Army of praying ſervent Souls, may do great Service in this Publick Cauſe. Pray and cry daily and mightily with God: Wreſtle with God in his own Power; and when God is with us, no Man can prevail againſt us.</p>
               <p>Two Words more muſt be added to quicken us:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Apprehenſions of the dreadful Conſequences of the Extinction of the Lamp of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at Home, which viſibly appears to every conſidering Mind. Our Enemies, the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers at Home, are now weak, but would ſoon lift up their Horns on high, and a Spirit of Perſecution enter into them, and this quickly enraged by the Power of a King, who hath made himſelf odious to humane Nature for it. But we hope his Day is coming.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider the now languiſhing expiring Weakneſs of Proteſtant Churches and Countries Abroad. And both put together, did ever ſo many Intereſts meet in one Perſon, of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of ſo many Kinds, both Civil and Religious, as depend, under God, upon our King's Preſervation? O then let us truſt, and pray without ceaſing for him.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>And ſo, <hi rend="blackletterType">God ſave the King.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
